<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lesson of self-deniall, or, The true way to desirable beauty by John Collings ...</title>
            <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12766327</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12766327</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199320</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20533)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199320)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 377:12e or 1306:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lesson of self-deniall, or, The true way to desirable beauty by John Collings ...</title>
                  <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690.</author>
                  <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690. Five lessons for a Christian to learne.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 89 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich: Tomlins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Has special t.p. with imprint: Printed for Rich. Tomlins, 1649.</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 377:12e as the fourth part of Wing C5317 (Five lessons) and separately at reel 1306:2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Self-denial --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199320:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A LESSON OF SELF-DENIALL:</hi> OR, <hi>The true way to deſirable BEAUTY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By JOHN COLLINGS,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 37.</bibl> He that loveth father or mother more than me, is not worthy of me; and he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſon or daughter more than me, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of me.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 38.</bibl> And he that taketh not up his croſſe, and followeth after me, is not worthy of me.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for</hi> Rich: Tomlins. 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:199320:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199320:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable, The Lady <hi>Frances Cecill,</hi> the only Daughter of the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe Dowager of <hi>EXETER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Increaſe of true Honour, and Peace, and Happineſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the plenty of <hi>Goſpell-ſheaves,</hi> which the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Lord</hi> of the <hi>Harveſt</hi> hath in our days cauſed his <hi>reapers</hi> to <hi>bind</hi> up,
<pb facs="tcp:199320:3"/> I could not but queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my <hi>gleane</hi> were worth your <hi>Ladiſhips</hi> ſtooping to take up. God hath ſeemed to empty his <hi>treaſuries</hi> upon our <hi>heads,</hi> that there is ſcarce a <hi>goſpell-duty</hi> but ſome or other more eminent <hi>labourers</hi> in the Lords <hi>harveſt</hi> have <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken</hi> to <hi>diſcover</hi> and <hi>urge,</hi> which makes me ſometimes <hi>tremble</hi> to think at what <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage</hi> they muſt periſh, that are yet dead or <hi>unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> But if there be any <hi>leſſon</hi> that hath been <hi>leſſer</hi> urged, or <hi>practiſed</hi> than <hi>other,</hi> it is this of <hi>ſelfe Deniall.</hi> I rejoyce to ſee the <hi>flowings of</hi> the <hi>ſpirit of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:199320:3"/> 
               <hi>grace</hi> in thoſe <hi>eminent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> of the Lord, that have both <hi>hunted</hi> for <hi>veniſon,</hi> and <hi>caught</hi> it, to make <hi>ſavory meat</hi> for the <hi>Saints,</hi> diſcovering thoſe <hi>ſecrets</hi> of the Lords <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and unſearchable <hi>riches</hi> of love, beyond the <hi>pennes or tongues</hi> of thoſe that have gone <hi>before</hi> them. But methinkes, I have ſometimes feared leſt while thoſe <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> ones have <hi>driven</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>peace</hi> of their <hi>own ſoules,</hi> and made it their <hi>work</hi> almoſt onely to dreſſe out the <hi>ſtrong meat,</hi> they ſhould have <hi>driven</hi> beyond the <hi>pace</hi> of the <hi>Lambs,</hi> and onely <hi>go</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb facs="tcp:199320:4"/> with <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>flock</hi> who are <hi>able</hi> to receive and <hi>have eares to heare,</hi> ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime <hi>goſpell myſteries.</hi> I have ſometimes wiſhed a <hi>Shepard</hi> or <hi>Hooker,</hi> or two more to ſtay behind, and to drive the <hi>remnant</hi> of the flock, which in <hi>heaven</hi> will <hi>overtake</hi> the other, though there be many things to be ſpoken which (without <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver driving</hi> them) they are not yet <hi>able</hi> to beare. I (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>one borne out of due time)</hi> am onely <hi>fit</hi> for ſuch a <hi>work,</hi> the opening the <hi>Rudiments</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and it ſhall be my <hi>crowne</hi> if by teaching the
<pb facs="tcp:199320:4"/> A B C of the <hi>wayes</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> I may be made <hi>inſtrumentall</hi> but to fit <hi>Saints</hi> for their <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchooles.</hi> I have preſumed here to preſent your <hi>Honour</hi> with the firſt <hi>Leſſon of Grace. He that will be my diſciple</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>let him deny himſelfe, and take up the croſſe and follow me;</hi> firſt <hi>deny himſelf,</hi> then <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me.</hi> Not but that I hope your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> can readily <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſe</hi> this <hi>ſermon,</hi> with that ſpeech of the young man, <hi>All theſe have I kept from my youth.</hi> Though I need not mind your <hi>Honour,</hi> that it is a <hi>lif's</hi> not a <hi>dayes</hi> practice. (Madam) there can be no
<pb facs="tcp:199320:5"/> 
               <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> like <hi>Experience,</hi> which eaſily convinceth me, that your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> (who have had a conſtant <hi>ſight</hi> of <hi>ſublunary</hi> vanities, an <hi>enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>creature-contentments)</hi> is farre more <hi>able</hi> to read him (who now writes) a lecture of the <hi>Vanity</hi> of <hi>every thing under the</hi> Sun, than he is to read it your <hi>Ladiſhip,</hi> who hath been <hi>bleſt</hi> in the <hi>want</hi> of thoſe <hi>advantages,</hi> and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (from a <hi>gueſſe</hi> at the <hi>body</hi> by the <hi>foot)</hi> can ſubſcribe <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> account of them: ſurely (Madam) there is nothing <hi>under the Sun,</hi> but in <hi>cleaving</hi> to it, and <hi>neglecting</hi> Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:199320:5"/> a rationall creature muſt <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour</hi> himſelfe as well as his <hi>Saviour,</hi> and as well call in queſtion his own <hi>judgement,</hi> and out-law his owne <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> as <hi>diſobey</hi> his God. Chriſt, (Madam!) Ah! <hi>Chriſt, Chriſt</hi> alone is the <hi>excelling</hi> one; that is <hi>Altogether deſires;</hi> It is the <hi>Roſe of Sharon</hi> only that wants <hi>prickles.</hi> His <hi>name</hi> is the onely box of <hi>Ointment,</hi> which one <hi>fly</hi> or other will not make to <hi>ſtinke.</hi> And now I mention his <hi>name,</hi> I remember what the ſpouſe ſaith, <hi>Thy name is an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment powerd forth, therefore doe the Virgines love thee.</hi> Of
<pb facs="tcp:199320:6"/> thoſe <hi>Virgines,</hi> I truſt your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> is, thoſe that love Chriſt for the <hi>ointment of his name powred forth;</hi> (ſo I truſt hath the <hi>Ointment of grace powred</hi> upon that head from which you drew your <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall breath,</hi> ran downe to the <hi>ſkirts</hi> of all her <hi>Relations.) (Madam)</hi> This <hi>world</hi> is not ſo well <hi>bred,</hi> but in Chriſts wayes if your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to <hi>walk,</hi> you muſt expect to be a <hi>ſharer</hi> in the <hi>ſcoffs of</hi> thoſe that <hi>put out the finger</hi> at thoſe that run not with them <hi>to the ſame exceſſe of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot.</hi> I need not mind your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> of the <hi>Grace of our</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:199320:6"/> 
               <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently endured the croſſe</hi> and <hi>deſpiſed the ſhame</hi> for your <hi>ſake. (Madam)</hi> the <hi>wayes</hi> of Chriſt, the <hi>paths</hi> of <hi>holineſſe,</hi> are onely <hi>uncomely</hi> to thoſe before whoſe <hi>eyes</hi> the <hi>Devill</hi> hath caſt a <hi>miſt,</hi> and the <hi>God of this world hath blinded their eyes, lest the glorious light of of the goſpell ſhould ſhine upon them. If the King deſires our beauty,</hi> no matter, whether our <hi>rate</hi> be <hi>high</hi> or <hi>low</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>children of Vanity, whoſe God is their Belly,</hi> and <hi>whoſe glory is their ſhame.</hi> May your Ladiſhip <hi>strive af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perfection,</hi> and yet <hi>daunce</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:199320:7"/> before the <hi>Ark,</hi> though <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal</hi> mocks <hi>out at the window<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The <hi>Moone</hi> keeps its <hi>courſe</hi> though the <hi>dogs bark.</hi> This Sermon <hi>(Madam)</hi> was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>dedicated</hi> to your <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips eares,</hi> I never thought then, that the noiſe of it ſhould have gone beyond the <hi>chappell</hi> it was <hi>preacht</hi> in, nor indeed had it, had not your <hi>Ladiſhips</hi> noble <hi>Mother</hi> commanded the tranſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a <hi>coppy,</hi> which deſire was alſo <hi>ſeconded</hi> by other <hi>Noble</hi> friends, whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands I was as <hi>unwilling</hi> to <hi>diſobey,</hi> as <hi>unable</hi> to <hi>performe,</hi> through my multitude of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:199320:7"/> 
               <hi>occaſions,</hi> which is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſon of my <hi>publication</hi> of it, that I might be <hi>thrifty</hi> of my <hi>time</hi> for my other <hi>ſtudies,</hi> and by <hi>troubling</hi> the <hi>world</hi> worke my own <hi>eaſe.</hi> Having reſolved upon this courſe, I was deſirous it ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare as <hi>covertly</hi> as might be, and have therefore added it to ſome other <hi>Sermons,</hi> preacht long before then, ſent to the <hi>preſſe</hi> to gratify the <hi>deſire</hi> of the <hi>Printer.</hi> (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam) your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> I truſt will eaſily excuſe me for the want of <hi>paines</hi> in it; If <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſpend time to <hi>tickle</hi> ſome few <hi>ears,</hi> it would <hi>be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftily</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:199320:8"/> done, and poſſibly <hi>I</hi> might by it loſe the <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> of ſpeaking to many an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others <hi>heart;</hi> I had rather ſo <hi>preach</hi> and <hi>write</hi> that thoſe that <hi>heare or read</hi> my <hi>ſermons,</hi> ſhould read and heare with a <hi>trembling heart,</hi> than with a <hi>tickled fancy.</hi> (Madam) Such as it is) I crave leave to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to your <hi>Ladiſhip,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching the God of grace ſo to empower every line, that it may be a <hi>drop of mercy</hi> to your <hi>Honours,</hi> and every <hi>Readers</hi> ſoule, That your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> may grow up <hi>like the tree planted by the rivers of water,</hi> and bring forth <hi>fruit</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:199320:8"/> 
               <hi>in your ſeaſon,</hi> That in the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing</hi> of every <hi>week,</hi> there may appeare in your <hi>Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips heart</hi> &amp; <hi>converſation,</hi> an anſwer of thoſe <hi>old prayers</hi> newly returned to your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips <hi>Noble Parent.</hi> That the Lord may have <hi>glory,</hi> your ſoule <hi>peace,</hi> and hee the dayly anſwer of his <hi>prayers,</hi> who truely is <hi>Madam,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humbly obliged ſervant in the Lord Jeſus, <hi>John Collings.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Chaplyfield houſe, <date>Aug: 21. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:199320:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199320:9"/>
            <head>A LESSON OF <hi>Self-Denyall.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 45. 10, 11.</bibl>
               <q>Hearken O daughter, and conſider, and encline thine eare: Forget alſo thy own people, and thy Fathers houſe, ſo ſhall the King deſire thy beauty,—</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is agreed (almoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all Expoſitors) that this <hi>Pſalme</hi> is a <hi>Marriage-Song,</hi> and principally relating to the <hi>ſpirituall marriage</hi> between <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>beleeving</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:199320:10"/> 
               <hi>ſoule,</hi> or between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Church:</hi> But there is a little <hi>queſtion</hi> amongſt them, whether the ſpirituall ſenſe of it be couched under a <hi>type,</hi> or an <hi>Allegory;</hi> Some thinke that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> here <hi>treates</hi> of that <hi>ſpirituall marriage,</hi> under the <hi>type</hi> of Solomons <hi>marriage</hi> to <hi>Pharaohs daughter,</hi> of which wee read, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 11. Of this opinion (ſaith D. <hi>Rivet)</hi> are <note place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Rivet <hi>Pref. in hunc Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum.</hi>
               </note> the Hebrew Interpreters, and moſt others, as <hi>Calvin, Bucer, Junius, Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenius.</hi> &amp;c. yet theſe grant that there are ſome things in the <hi>Pſalme</hi> not capable of that <hi>literall ſenſe.</hi> Others are againſt this, partly becauſe (as they ſay) that <hi>marriage</hi> of Solomons was <hi>wicked,</hi> and againſt Gods <hi>Law,</hi> Deut. 7. and partly becauſe it is probable that <hi>Solomon</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving before that time (as 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 3.) the <hi>feare of the Lord</hi> in his <hi>heart,</hi> it is not probable he would have <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> that <hi>marriage,</hi> had not ſhe firſt <hi>contracted</hi> to have <hi>forſaken</hi> her <hi>fathers houſe</hi> (which the Hebrewes alſo ſay was one of the <hi>marriage-Articles.)</hi> But it is probable that that <hi>marriage</hi> gave occaſion to the writing of this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199320:10"/> 
               <hi>Pſalme;</hi> and for the reaſon againſt it, <hi>Rivet</hi> anſwers by a Rule of S. <hi>Hieroms,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Homines mali in re non bona, ſanctiſſima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum rerum imo ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius Dei <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi eſſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt.</note> That <hi>In Scripture, evill men, and that in wicked actions, are oft-times types of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly actions, and that of Gods owne too oft times; Iſhmael</hi> was a <hi>type</hi> of the <hi>old Teſtament</hi> (according to the Apoſtle) an many other inſtances might bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Whether it be a <hi>Type</hi> or an <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> is not much <hi>materiall,</hi> nor worth the <hi>disputing: Rivet</hi> thinks neither ſenſe improbable, but conceives it might be both; nor do I ſee any thing of value againſt it. In the <hi>Pſalme</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Preface,</hi> verſe 1. Wherein he Pſalmiſt declares the <hi>readineſſe</hi> of his <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>inſtinct</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him upon the <hi>Compoſure</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>narrative part of the Pſalm,</hi> from the 2 verſe to the laſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Concluſion of it,</hi> verſe <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>narrative part</hi> is ſomething, 1. Relating to the <hi>Bridegroom.</hi> 2. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the <hi>Bride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Bridegroome</hi> is <hi>commended</hi> from his <hi>Beauty,</hi> v. 2. <hi>Thou art fairer than</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199320:11"/> 
               <hi>the children of men.</hi> 2. From his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence,</hi> v. 2. <hi>Grace is powred into thy lips.</hi> 3. From the <hi>bleſſing of God</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; <hi>God hath bleſſed thee for ever.</hi> 4. From <hi>his Glory and Majeſty,</hi> v. 3. 5. From <hi>his ſucceſſe,</hi> v. 4. 6. From <hi>his Temper and Diſpoſition,</hi> verſe 4. 7. From <hi>his Valour,</hi> verſe 4, 5, 6. 8. From <hi>the nature of his Kingdome,</hi> v. 6. 9. From <hi>his love to Juſtice,</hi> v. 7. 10. From <hi>the perfume of his Garments,</hi> v. 8. 11. From <hi>his choice in his Queene</hi> and his <hi>Attendants,</hi> v. 9. So farre it relates to the <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other part relates to the <hi>Bride;</hi> and in it is a Leſſon of <hi>Inſtruction</hi> and <hi>Exhortation</hi> read to her, preſt from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>Motives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Exhortation</hi> is in the two ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in which my Text lyes; And it is <hi>foure-fold,</hi> preſt from ſeverall <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> In the Text then you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, 1. An <hi>Exhortation,</hi> enforced upon the former <hi>Deſcription.</hi> 2. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>Motives</hi> to preſſe this <hi>Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:199320:11"/>
               <head>1. In the firſt conſider,</head>
               <item>1. <hi>The perſon exhorted;</hi> ſet out by the name of <hi>Daughter, (O Daughter.)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation;</hi> which is <hi>five-fold:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Hearken.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Conſider.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Incline thin eare.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Forget</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>thy people and thy fa, thers houſe.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Worſhip him.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. The <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it, which are,
<list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>former deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him;</hi> now thou art married to ſuch an husband, <hi>hearken, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The <hi>Relation</hi> of <hi>Daughter;</hi> Children ſhould harken to their <hi>Parents.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Shee ſhould bee <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. Her <hi>beauty</hi> ſhould be <hi>deſireable.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. The <hi>King ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it;</hi> yea, <hi>greatly deſire her beauty.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199320:12"/>
            <p> Let me a little open the words, and then proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[O Daughter,] Quae conſentit viro in matrimonium eſt viro in loco filiae,</hi> ſaith <hi>Rivet:</hi> The woman that conſents to her <hi>Husband</hi> in marriage, is to him in ſtead of a <hi>Daughter:</hi> So ſaith the <hi>Parable,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 12. 3. The <hi>Ewe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lambe,</hi> which ſignified the <hi>wife,</hi> laid in the poore mans <hi>boſome,</hi> and was unto him <hi>as a daughter,</hi> Jer. 3. 4. <hi>Wilt thou not from hence forth crie unto me, Thou art my Father, the guide of my youth,</hi> the <hi>guide of her youth,</hi> that is, an <hi>Husband,</hi> and yet her <hi>Father.</hi> God can <hi>marry</hi> his <hi>Daughter,</hi> and yet the marriage not be <hi>inceſtuous;</hi> Yea, hee firſt marryes the <hi>ſoule,</hi> and then makes it his <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> according to that 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 18. <hi>Wherefore come out from amongſt them, and be yee ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and I will be a Father unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou, and you ſhal be to me Sonnes and Daughters,</hi> ſaith the Lord; Daughters by <hi>Adoption, Gal.</hi> 4. 6. Nor in vaine called a Daughter: It is a <hi>courteous compellation,</hi> as both <hi>Rivet</hi> and <hi>Mollerus</hi> note, by which the Lord will let his <hi>Saints</hi> know, that he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199320:12"/> will <hi>extend</hi> towards them the <hi>care</hi> of a <hi>father,</hi> as well as the <hi>love</hi> of an <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> he will <hi>love them</hi> like an <hi>husband,</hi> and <hi>protect</hi> them like a <hi>father.</hi> Hearke Chriſtians! <hi>Saints are Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> as wel as <hi>Spouſes to Chriſt.</hi> If he be a <hi>father where is his honour?</hi> If an husband <hi>where his love?</hi> But to proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hearken</hi> O Daughter] <hi>Audi filia,]</hi> What ſhould ſhee heare? Shee ſhould heare her <hi>husband.</hi> There <hi>was a voice from heaven,</hi> Matth. 17. 5. <hi>This is my well-beloved Son heare him.</hi> Chriſts Sheep are eare-marked, <hi>John</hi> 10. 11. The good ſheep are thus markt, <hi>They hear his voice.</hi> Faith comes <hi>by hearing,</hi> yea and it growes up by <hi>hearing</hi> too; they are over-growne <hi>Saints</hi> that are growne paſt <hi>Ordinances,</hi> I am afraid they are growne out of <hi>Chriſts know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> it is the <hi>deafe adder ſtops her eare. Davids</hi> eare was <hi>opened,</hi> Pſal. 40. They that are too proud to <hi>heare Chriſts Voice</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> I am afraid will be thought too <hi>vile</hi> ever to <hi>ſee his face in heaven. Hearken therefore (O Daughter)</hi> Gods way to the <hi>Heart</hi> lies through the <hi>Eare,</hi> that's his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199320:13"/> 
               <hi>way;</hi> if he at any time comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>way,</hi> I am afraid it is not when wee have wilfully blockt that up, but when himſelfe hath ſtopt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hearken O Daughter,</hi> and <hi>Conſider, or ſee] &amp; vide:</hi> Firſt <hi>heare,</hi> then <hi>ſee.</hi> There is a <hi>ſeeing</hi> of <hi>Faith. Faith</hi> is the daughter of <hi>hearing;</hi> the <hi>Eare</hi> muſt open before the <hi>ſoule.</hi> Doe not onely <hi>heare</hi> but alſo <hi>ſee. Hearing</hi> is not enough. <hi>He that beleeveth not, is damned already. Seeing</hi> may bee of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. As wee have heard, ſo have we ſeene in the City of our God.</hi> The ſoule that <hi>heares</hi> well ſhall <hi>ſee. Iohn</hi> 1. 50. <hi>Becauſe I ſaid unto thee, I ſaw thee under the Fig-tree, beleeveſt thou? thou ſhalt ſee greater things than theſe.</hi> Faith muſt goe before <hi>Sight,</hi> but <hi>Sight</hi> ſhall <hi>ſucceed</hi> faith: yet <hi>Faith</hi> is a <hi>Sight,</hi> though not of <hi>experience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And incline thine eare.]</hi> Expoſitors make this Phraſe to containe three things. 1. <hi>A Repetition</hi> of the firſt Branch, <hi>Hearken.</hi> It is a difficult <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> the word is <hi>doubled,</hi> that it may bee <hi>inforced;</hi> the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaks twice, conſidering our <hi>deafneſſe,</hi> yet he ſpeaks
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199320:13"/> 
               <hi>louder</hi> in this than in the other <hi>phraſe.</hi> Secondly, therefore <hi>To incline the eare,</hi> is <hi>more</hi> than to <hi>heare,</hi> it doth argue a notable <hi>ſtirring of Attention.</hi> Hee that <hi>inclines</hi> his eare, <hi>affert al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi motum &amp; propenſionem,</hi> quickens up his <hi>minde,</hi> and brings with him to the duty a <hi>readineſſe of Spirit,</hi> and an <hi>intentneſſe of minde.</hi> 3. Inclining the <hi>Eare</hi> ſay ſome is <hi>Nota demiſſionis,</hi> a Note of that <hi>ſubjection</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> which ſhould bee found in the <hi>Spouſe of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> toward him. It followeth in the Text,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And forget thine owne people, and thy Fathers houſe.]</hi> Here are two things to be enquired into. 1. What is meant <hi>by her owne People, and her Fathers Houſe.</hi> 2. What is meant <hi>by forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them.</hi> For the firſt, we muſt be guided by the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Spouſe,</hi> to whom theſe words are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; if you look upon, 1. The <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jewes</hi> as the <hi>Spouſe</hi> meant here to be <hi>married</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion it is meant of the <hi>Jewiſh Worſhip.</hi> the <hi>Ceremoniall Law and Worſhip,</hi> and their <hi>Traditions,</hi> they were to bee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199320:14"/> 
               <hi>forgotten,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpell-worſhip</hi> to be embraced; the worſhip of Chriſts <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, conſonant</hi> to that of Chriſt to the Woman of <hi>Samarta, John</hi> 4. 21, 22, 23. 2. If you underſtond by the <hi>Spouſe, the Church of the Gentiles,</hi> then the <hi>Fathers houſe</hi> is all the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile worſhip and Paganiſh Idolatry,</hi> which muſt all be left upon their <hi>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Chriſt.</hi> 3. If you underſtand by the Spouſe the particular <hi>beleeving ſoule,</hi> the <hi>Fathers houſe,</hi> is <hi>old Adams houſe,</hi> all <hi>ſinnne</hi> and <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> all <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall worſhipping. Renounce</hi> the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Per patris domum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligo, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ex u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero afferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, aut quaecunque ex prava in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione nobis adhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent quaſi ad nos hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditario ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re aut edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione transfuſa.</hi> Rivet <hi>ad loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>World</hi> (ſaith <hi>Deodate)</hi> and cleave to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> It is a Leſſon of <hi>Selfe-Deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> conſonant to that of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 37. By Fathers houſe, ſaith Doctor <hi>Rivet,</hi> wee may underſtand whatever corruption wee either brought out of the wombe with us, or have contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by ill education or cuſtome, ſo that they cleave to us as our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And by <hi>People,</hi> ſaith he, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>[ea quae ex mala conſuetudine, &amp; converſatione cum impiis acquiſita, nos a Deo abducunt, quae omnia nobis ſunt deponenda]</hi> all thoſe <hi>Corruptions,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:199320:14"/> and whatever they be, which we have contracted by ill <hi>acquaintance,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing</hi> amongſt the <hi>wicked,</hi> which <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrange</hi> us from <hi>God,</hi> theſe muſt all bee laid downe, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 26. I ſhall anon in the opening of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, open this tearm more fully. I now proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So ſhall the King deſire thy Beauty.]</hi> Some read it, <hi>Quia concupivit,</hi> becauſe the <hi>King</hi> hath <hi>deſired</hi> thy <hi>beauty,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it a <hi>motive</hi> to induce her to <hi>forget her fathers houſe.</hi> So <hi>Auguſt. Cyprian, &amp;c.</hi> Others read it, according to our <hi>Tranſlation, [The King]</hi> The King of Glory, the <hi>King of Peace, Chriſt</hi> that King. <hi>I have ſet my King upon my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hill of Zion:</hi> Hee is the King, [Greatly deſire] Out of his <hi>love</hi> to thee, his <hi>great love to thee,</hi> he ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it; not onely <hi>love</hi> thee, but <hi>deſire</hi> thee; yea not onely <hi>deſire</hi> thee, but <hi>greatly deſire thee.</hi> He ſpeaks after the <hi>manner of men,</hi> whoſe <hi>deſire is to the women</hi> they <hi>love, Gen.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee ſhall be his deſire.</hi> And ſo, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 11. <hi>If thou ſeeſt amongſt the Captives a beautifull woman, and thou haſt a deſire</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:199320:15"/> 
               <hi>to her to make her thy wife.</hi> Chriſts <hi>Love</hi> is ſuch to the ſoule, that he hath a <hi>deſire to her,</hi> yea not a <hi>deſire</hi> barely, but a <hi>paſſionate deſire, he ſhall greatly deſire,</hi> he ſhall be <hi>in love</hi> with the <hi>ſoule. [He ſhall greatly deſire thy Beauty.]</hi> What <hi>Beauty? Pulchritudo eſt in mente cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentium,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Muſculus)</hi> it is meant not of a face Beauty, but an heart Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Decor Eccleſiae</hi> (ſaith <hi>Mollerus) eſt in fide, obedientia, &amp; dilectione.</hi> In the graces of the ſoule, it is a Beauty that the Lord Chriſt puts upon the ſoule, it is not a Beauty of nature, but of grace that is the Saints Beauty: <hi>Sanctitas Eccleſiae eſt pulchritudo Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia</hi> (ſaith <hi>Piſcator)</hi> the <hi>holineſſe</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> is the <hi>Churches beauty,</hi> and ſo the <hi>holines</hi> of the <hi>ſoul</hi> is the <hi>ſouls beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> This is the <hi>fairenes,</hi> this the <hi>Beauty</hi> that is meant in thoſe places of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Song,</hi> Cant. 1. 10, 11. Cant. 4. 1. Cant. 6. 1. Cant. 7. 1. This is the <hi>Beauty</hi> that the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>great King ſhall ſo deſire</hi> in the ſoule, this is the <hi>comelineſſe</hi> that ſhall make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>poore ſoule deſireable in the eyes</hi> of the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> This is the <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:199320:15"/> which will make the King of <hi>Glory reſt</hi> and <hi>content</hi> himſelfe in his <hi>Love</hi> to the <hi>ſoule</hi> that hath it, and make him bee <hi>delighted</hi> with the <hi>acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the ſoule,</hi> and in <hi>converſing,</hi> and having <hi>Communion</hi> with the <hi>ſoule.</hi> This is it that which (where it is found) will ſo <hi>raviſh</hi> Chriſts <hi>heart,</hi> that he will never <hi>part from the ſoule</hi> (as <hi>Mollerus</hi> expounds that phraſe <hi>[greatly deſire.]</hi> Thus (as ſhortly as I could diſpatch it) you have the ſenſe of the Text. Now in it there lyes theſe truths.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the gracious ſoule, by mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to Jeſus Chriſt, becomes his Daughter as well as his Spouſe.</hi> Hee will not onely love her as a Wife, but care for her as a Daughter, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2, <hi>That it is a great piece of the Daughters worke to hearken to Chriſt in his Word.</hi> It is no height of Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to be beyond <hi>Ordinances,</hi> if wee be out of Heaven: It is a note of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate,</hi> being once enlightned, to <hi>fall back;</hi> but it is a new degree of Saintship; they are <hi>deafe Adders,</hi> that have lived thus long no Saints; Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199320:16"/> of the <hi>Devill,</hi> not of <hi>God;</hi> his <hi>Daughters</hi> muſt <hi>hearken. [Hearken O Daughter.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Chriſts Daughter muſt and ſhall ſee as well as heare.</hi> Hearing is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; the ſoule muſt be <hi>open</hi> to <hi>receive Chriſt</hi> as well as the <hi>eare</hi> to <hi>heare</hi> his <hi>voice,</hi> and if they will <hi>heare,</hi> they ſhall <hi>ſee. [Hearken O Daughter, and ſee.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Chriſts Daughters muſt incline their eare as well as heare and ſee. Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> muſt bee joyn'd to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip.</hi> Inward <hi>affection</hi> and <hi>intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of minde</hi> muſt bee <hi>joyned</hi> with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>hearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Which is the Doctrine I will In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That ſoule that would have the Lord Jeſus Chriſt deſire its beauty, muſt forget its owne people, and its Fathers Houſe. And whoſoever doth that ſhall bee beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Lord Jeſus ſhall deſire its Beauty.</hi> In the handling of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I ſhall doe theſe 5 things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199320:16"/> 1. <hi>I ſhall ſhew you what it is for a ſoule to forget its owne people, and its Fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I ſhall ſhew you how, and in what ſenſe the ſoule that doth it ſhall be beautifull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>I ſhall ſhew what is meant by the Lord Chriſts deſiring ſuch a ſoules beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>I ſhall give you ſome reaſons, why it is requiſite that the ſoule that would endeare it ſelfe to Chriſt, and make it ſelfe deſireable, ſhould forget its Fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, I ſhall <hi>apply</hi> the whole <hi>Doctrine</hi> ſuitably.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what is meant by the ſoules <hi>owne people,</hi> and <hi>Fathers houſe;</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>by forgetting of them.</hi> What was meant in generall I ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Our Fathers houſe is old <hi>Adams</hi> houſe, the world and all therein. I ſhall now ſhew you in ſome particulars, Firſt, <hi>What of our Eathers muſt bee forgot.</hi> Secondly, <hi>how and in what ſenſe we muſt forget it.</hi> The firſt I ſhall diſpatch in theſe few following par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, as briefely as I can.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199320:17"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>The ſoule muſt forget the manners of its Fathers houſe.</hi> Our Fathers houſe (ever ſince God and hee parted <hi>houſes</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe)</hi> is an houſe of ill <hi>manners,</hi> an houſe of <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>wickedneſſe.</hi> Now every ſoule that would make it ſelfe <hi>beautions</hi> or <hi>deſireable</hi> in the ſight of <hi>Chriſts eyes,</hi> muſt <hi>ſhake hands</hi> with <hi>ſin. Iſ.</hi> 55. 7. <hi>Let the wicked man forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and let him returne to the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and unto our God, and he will abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pardon him;</hi> ay then the King ſhall deſire his beauty, but firſt let him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the <hi>manners</hi> of his <hi>Fathers houſe.</hi> All ſinne muſt bee forgotten: But I take it eſpecially foure ſorts of ſinnes are hinted to us in this Phraſe, and may more properly be called the ſinnes of our Fathers houſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Originall ſinne.</hi> If we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of Grace or Goodneſſe, wee never learn'd that at <hi>home.</hi> It is the <hi>gift of God</hi> through the <hi>tutoring</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> But for Sinne, wee need not goe abroad to <hi>learne</hi> that, it was <hi>bred in the bone,</hi> that's one reaſon why it will <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199320:17"/> 
               <hi>out of the fleſh,</hi> Ez. 16. <hi>Tby Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was an Amorite, and thy Mother an Hittite.</hi> We are chilnren of <hi>wrath by nature,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 3. Pſal. 51. 4. <hi>In ſinne did my mother conceive me;</hi> Now this muſt be forgotten; this is a piece of our <hi>Fathers houſe.</hi> Men and Women you know are uſually borne in their <hi>Fathers Houſe;</hi> We are all <hi>borne</hi> in the <hi>houſe of bondage,</hi> which muſt be <hi>forgotten,</hi> if ever the ſoule be <hi>deſireable to Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It is a uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſaying of Divines, that <hi>he that was never truely humbled for Originall ſinne, was never truely humbled for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſinnes of our Education.</hi> The Fathers houſe is the houſe where the Childe is brought up: All ſinne is not bred in us; that which is bred in us may bee <hi>improved. Originall ſinne</hi> is ſinne in the <hi>ſeed; Actuall ſinne</hi> is ſinne in the <hi>Blade</hi> and <hi>Fruit.</hi> The World is a <hi>duſty houſe,</hi> you can ſet a <hi>Creature</hi> in never a <hi>corner of it,</hi> but it will <hi>contract</hi> ſome <hi>duſt. Joſeph</hi> by being in the King of <hi>Egypts houſe,</hi> learn'd to ſweare by his <hi>Maſters life.</hi> According to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199320:18"/> 
               <hi>breedings,</hi> are men addicted to <hi>different Vanities,</hi> whether <hi>pleaſure,</hi> or <hi>honour, &amp;c.</hi> Now when the ſoul comes unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> he muſt come off theſe, he muſt forget his <hi>Fathers houſe,</hi> all his vaine ſinfull <hi>breeding,</hi> and all the filth his ſoule hath <hi>contracted</hi> by reaſon of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Sinnes of Converſation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</hi> The Fathers houſe, and the company of it, is the childs <hi>company,</hi> thoſe of his Fathers houſe, are his owne <hi>people.</hi> It is true, as well for Religion as any thing elſe, <hi>Magni refert quibuſcum convixeris.</hi> It is a great matter with whom we <hi>converſe;</hi> from accompanying with vaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, thou ſhalt learne to bee <hi>vaine: Cum lupis ululare.</hi> When the ſoule comes to Chriſt, it muſt leave all; ſins thus <hi>contracted,</hi> they are part of the <hi>manders of the Fathers Houſe. Paul</hi> left his <hi>Phariſaiſme</hi> that he had <hi>learnt</hi> at <hi>Gamaliels</hi> feet.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Cuſtomary ſinnes muſt bee left.</hi> The Child learnes cuſtomes in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe. <hi>Cuſtomary ſinning</hi> muſt be left of that ſoule that would render
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199320:18"/> it ſelfe for beauty <hi>deſireable to Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> Thoſe ſinnes which are to the ſoule as the <hi>Leopards ſpot,</hi> and the <hi>blacknes</hi> of the <hi>blackamores skinne.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this is hard; Cuſtome hatcheth a <hi>ſecond nature,</hi> Jer. 13. 23. <hi>How can you that are accuſtomed to doe evill, do well?</hi> Yet it muſt bee done, the <hi>Fathers houſe</hi> muſt be <hi>forgotten:</hi> ill cuſtomes <hi>muſt be laid aſide,</hi> or good ones wil not be <hi>taken up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Beloved ſinnes</hi> muſt be left. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing of the <hi>Fathers Houſe</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt is deare to the child. But the deareſt ſinne muſt bee ſhaken hands with, Matth. 18. 9. If it bee <hi>a right hand</hi> it muſt be <hi>cut off:</hi> if a <hi>right eye,</hi> it muſt be <hi>pluckt out.</hi> Our Members muſt be <hi>Mortified,</hi> Col. 3. 5. Thus the maners of our Fathers houſe muſt be forgotten. <hi>All ſinnes,</hi> but eſpecially theſe ſinnes. I proceed now.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſoule muſt forget <hi>the Company of its Fathers houſe.</hi> What is that you will ſay? I will anſwer you in two particulars. 1. <hi>Our moſt near and deareſt Relations.</hi> See <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 16. <hi>If a man commeth to me</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199320:19"/> Chriſt) <hi>and hateth not Father, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Children, and Brethren, and Wife, and Sisters, yea and his own life alſo, he is not worthy of mee.</hi> He ſhall not bee ſo beautifull; not ſo beautifull, as that <hi>the King ſhall deſire his beauty.</hi> As it was ſaid <hi>Levi</hi> did in another ſenſe, ſo muſt the Saint doe in ſome ſenſe: He muſt ſay <hi>unto his Father, and to his Mother, I have not ſeen him,</hi> neither muſt hee acknowledge <hi>his Brethren, nor know his owne children.</hi> Otherwiſe he will never have <hi>Levie's</hi> Character, to bee one that obſerveth the <hi>Lords Word and keeps his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> Not that Religion <hi>teacheth,</hi> or <hi>commandeth,</hi> or <hi>indureth</hi> a Saint to <hi>break</hi> the tyes of <hi>all Religion;</hi> No, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it doth not diſcharge a <hi>Saint of his Duty of Nature;</hi> it puts in a Plea alſo againſt ſuch <hi>unnaturalneſſe; Honour thy Father and Mother, &amp;c.</hi> is the fifth Commandement, the <hi>firſt with promiſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it allow a <hi>Saint</hi> to rob his <hi>parents</hi> of their due, with ſaying, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> it is a gift: <hi>The Ravens of the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys ſhall picke out the eyes of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:199320:19"/> as well as the <hi>Devill</hi> hath done of their <hi>Religion.</hi> Neither doth it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a Saint of his <hi>providentiall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and reſpect to his <hi>relation. Hee that provides not for his Family is worſe than an Infidell.</hi> 1. In point of <hi>due honour.</hi> 2. In point of <hi>naturall affection.</hi> 3. In point of <hi>Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall care.</hi> Wee muſt not forget the <hi>Company</hi> of our <hi>Fathers Houſe.</hi> Gods Commands doe not enterfiere, nor will the <hi>Gospell</hi> in that caſe give a <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſedeas</hi> to the <hi>Law.</hi> But 1. <hi>if God and they draw ſeverall wayes,</hi> if the Parents commands croſſe Gods, then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>It is better to obey God than men:</hi> The <hi>Parent</hi> is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <hi>for God,</hi> not <hi>againſt</hi> him, <hi>ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately,</hi> not <hi>ſupremely;</hi> he muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed for <hi>Gods ſake,</hi> and God too for <hi>his ſake,</hi> as by his <hi>command</hi> he ſeconds <hi>God;</hi> but <hi>Parents</hi> can as <hi>little,</hi> yea leſs <hi>diſcharge</hi> the <hi>child</hi> of its <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> than the <hi>Pope</hi> can <hi>diſcharge</hi> the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of his <hi>Allegiance</hi> to his <hi>Prince.</hi> 2. <hi>If their love becken us out of the way when God calls us, or would intice us to make halts in our running through</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199320:20"/> 
               <hi>fire and water to him,</hi> then wee muſt forget them. I have ſomewhere met with a Speech of St. <hi>Hierome</hi> to that purpoſe: Saith hee, <hi>If the Lord Chriſt ſhould call me to him, though my Father ſhould lye in my way, and my Mother ſhould hang about my neck, I would goe over my Father, and ſhake off my Mother, and runne to my Chriſt. Shetterden</hi> a Martyr (as it is ſtoried of him) writ to his Mother thus; <hi>Dear Mother, imbrace the Counſell of Gods Word with Heart and Affection, read it with obedienee, ſo ſhall we meet in joy at the laſt day, Or elſe I bid you fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well for ever.</hi> In theſe now and ſuch like caſes, that ſoule that would make its beauty <hi>deſireable</hi> in the <hi>eyes</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> muſt like <hi>Levi</hi> ſay to his <hi>Father</hi> and his <hi>Mother, I have not ſeen you;</hi> in theſe caſes he muſt not <hi>acknowledge</hi> his <hi>Brethren,</hi> nor <hi>know his owne Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> They ſtand in Chriſts way, and Chriſt calls <hi>haſtily.</hi> The Saint muſt ſpare no time to <hi>parley. Naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> with them he muſt forget his <hi>Fathers houſe,</hi> the <hi>deare company of it, his Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199320:20"/>
            <p> Secondly, all <hi>ſinfull Company</hi> is the Company of our <hi>Fathers houſe,</hi> The Company of <hi>fooles,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> calls it. Now all this muſt be forgotten, or elſe in ſtead of <hi>being ſaved,</hi> thy ſoule will bee <hi>deſtroied.</hi> Prov. 13. 20. <hi>A Companion of fooles ſhall bee deſtroied.</hi> Pſalme 119. 63. <hi>I am a companion</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) of thoſe that fear thee.</hi> You muſt leave your <hi>ſwearing Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and your <hi>drinking Company,</hi> and your <hi>vain Company,</hi> or the King will never <hi>deſire</hi> your <hi>beauty.</hi> The ſoul that would render it ſelfe <hi>deſireable</hi> in the eyes of the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> muſt make all its delight, (with <hi>David)</hi> in thoſe that <hi>excell in vertue,</hi> the Saints upon the earth. <hi>Saul</hi> before his <hi>Converſion</hi> was a companion of thoſe that <hi>ſtoned Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> and perſecuted the <hi>Saints. Like to like,</hi> for himſelfe <hi>conſented to his death,</hi> and was a <hi>Perſecutor;</hi> but no ſooner had the Lord made his <hi>Motion</hi> to him, but he <hi>forgat this company,</hi> and aſſayed to <hi>joyne himſelfe to the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſoule that would ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its <hi>beauty deſireable in Jeſus</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:199320:21"/> 
               <hi>Chriſts eyes,</hi> muſt forget the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Pompe,</hi> and <hi>Riches and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Fathers houſe, all the high-Towers and Treaſures of it, &amp;c.</hi> They that will be Chriſts <hi>Diſciples</hi> muſt not take up <hi>Crownes,</hi> and <hi>advance</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and <hi>follow him:</hi> No, they muſt <hi>deny</hi> themſelves, and <hi>take up the croſſe and follow him;</hi> their Crownes muſt be of <hi>Thornes,</hi> made after their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <hi>Coppy:</hi> They muſt not be ſuch as love <hi>the uppermoſt roomes at Feaſts, and the chiefe ſeats of the Synagogues, and Greetings in the Market, and to be called of men</hi> Rabbi, Rabbi. <hi>Bee not yee call'd</hi> Rabbi (ſaith Chriſt) for <hi>one is your Maſter, even Chriſt, and all yee are brethren. Hee that is greateſt amongſt them that are Saints, muſt be as a Servant,</hi> Matth. 23. 7, 8, 9, 10. They muſt forget that <hi>naturall it ching</hi> which is in the children of <hi>Adam</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually, and muſt be ſcratched with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> or <hi>Rabbi,</hi> or ſome <hi>high-ſwelling words of vanity:</hi> they muſt not bee ſuch, as will ſwell (like that Toad <hi>Haman)</hi> if <hi>Mordecay</hi> give him not the <hi>knee,</hi> or if their <hi>Brother</hi> give them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199320:21"/> not the <hi>wall</hi> or the <hi>way;</hi> Saints are no ſuch <hi>creatures;</hi> they are ſuch as are not at all taken with any ſuch <hi>high ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> but Rom. 12. 10. <hi>In honour they prefer one before another.</hi> And they muſt look upon it as the greateſt <hi>honor</hi> in the <hi>world,</hi> not that they are <hi>maſters,</hi> and deſcended<hi>—atavis Regibus,</hi> of great Parentage. &amp;c. but that they are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> the name of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (the <hi>badge of honour</hi> firſt created at <hi>Antioch)</hi> muſt appeare to them, better than the names of <hi>Lord</hi> or <hi>Lady. Theodoſius</hi> was wont (they ſay) more to <hi>glory</hi> that hee was a <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Chriſt,</hi> than that hee was <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the Eaſt.</hi> Now I ſay, That ſoule that would make its <hi>beauty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable</hi> to Chriſt, muſt forget all theſe, not affect any of them, not value them; for <hi>hee that exalteth himſelfe ſhall bee abaſed, and he that humbleth himſelfe ſhall be exalted.</hi> Behold a <hi>miracle</hi> (ſaith <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 12.</note> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) God is an high God</hi> (yea, the moſt high) yet the <hi>higher</hi> thou lifteſt up thy ſelfe, the further thou art off him; the <hi>lower</hi> thou humbleſt thy ſelfe, the nearer he drawes to thee; he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199320:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> looks neare to the <hi>humble,</hi> that he may raiſe them up, but <hi>ſees the proud afarre off,</hi> that hee may <hi>depreſſe</hi> them. The <hi>proud Phariſee</hi> preſt as neare God as hee could, the <hi>poore Publican</hi> durſt not, but ſtood afarre off; God was <hi>farre from the one</hi> and <hi>neare to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The <hi>high towers</hi> of the <hi>fathers houſe</hi> muſt bee <hi>forgotten,</hi> yea, and ſo muſt all the <hi>rich coffins and cheſts of it:</hi> theſe are part of the <hi>furniture</hi> of our <hi>fathers houſe.</hi> You know what Chriſt ſaid to the young man, when he ſeemed to bee <hi>in love with Chriſt,</hi> Matth. 19. 21. <hi>If thou wilt be perfect,</hi> if thou wilt make thy beauty a deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beauty, <hi>Goe, and ſell all that thou haſt, and give to the poore, and thou ſhalt have treaſure in heaven, and come and follow mee,</hi> and againe v. 24. <hi>It is eaſier for a camell to goe through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> You know what Chriſt ſaies, Mat. 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the poore are thoſe that are goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized.</hi> But to proceed yet.</p>
            <p>The ſoule that would render its beauty deſirable in Chriſts eyes, muſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199320:22"/> forget <hi>the pleaſures and vanities of its fathers houſe,</hi> all that is in the world, 1 Joh. 2. 16. whether it be <hi>the luſt of the eyes, or the luſt of the fleſh, or the pride of life.</hi> When the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>lovers of pleaſures,</hi> he puts in <hi>more than lovers of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 4. <hi>Jude</hi> tels us, ſuch as are <hi>ſenſuall</hi> have not <hi>the ſpirit,</hi> Jude 18. 19. <hi>Iob</hi> in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the wicked, <hi>Job.</hi> 21. 12, 13. tels us, that they are ſuch as <hi>take up the tymbrell and harpe, and rejoyce at the ſound of the Organ, their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren dance, they ſpend their dayes in wealth, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are they <hi>that ſay unto God, Depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of his wayes. What is the Almighty that wee ſhould ſerve him? and what profit is there, that we ſhould pray unto him,</hi> v. 15. Their <hi>fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles</hi> muſt be laid in the <hi>water</hi> of <hi>true repentance</hi> and <hi>contrition.</hi> The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>pleaſure</hi> muſt <hi>undreſſe,</hi> if they will be <hi>beautifull</hi> in <hi>Chriſts</hi> eyes; they muſt lay aſide their <hi>paintings</hi> and <hi>dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,</hi> their <hi>curlings</hi> and <hi>perfumings of the haire,</hi> where (as hee wittily ſayes) <hi>the powder doth forget the duſt;</hi> their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199320:23"/> 
               <hi>ornament</hi> muſt not <hi>be the outward ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of plaiting the haire, and of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring gold, and putting on of apparell; but the hidden man of the heart in that which is not corruptible, even the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God of great price,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 3, 4. The <hi>daughters of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> muſt <hi>undreſſe</hi> (I ſay) for the Lord, as he threatned hee would doe in the day of judgement, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 3. 18, 19, 20. ſo in the day of mercy, to the ſoule of the vaine creature, hee will alſo <hi>take away the bravery of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eir tinckling or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments about their feet, and their cauls, and their round tyres like the moone, the chaines, and the bracelets, and the mufflers, the bonnets, and the ornaments of the legs, and the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and the tablets, and the eare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and the rings, and the noſe jewels, the changeable ſuits of apparell, and the mantles, and the wimples, and the criſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping pinnes, and the glaſſes, and the fine linnen, and the hoods, and the vailes, and inſtead of theſe ſend in mercy, a gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with ſackcloth, a rent heart, and a weeping eye, and a ſerious ſoule.</hi> It was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199320:23"/> a ſure rule that a Divine once gave to another, enquiring of him why he did not perſwade a <hi>Gentlewoman</hi> (with whom hee was acquainted) to leave off ſome vaine dreſſes ſhee wore; (Saith hee) <hi>I will firſt perſwade her to get Chriſt into her heart, and then ſhee will leave theſe of her ſelfe.</hi> The ſoul that hath Chriſt in his heart, need not to be perſwaded to leave its <hi>fidling</hi> and <hi>dancing,</hi> and <hi>love ſongs,</hi> and <hi>vaine dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>paintings,</hi> and <hi>revellings,</hi> and <hi>naked breaſts;</hi> it knowes theſe will not make its <hi>beauty deſirable</hi> in <hi>Chriſts eyes;</hi> and it is loſt labour to perſwade others to it. When <hi>Solomon forſooke</hi> God, then he ran to <hi>pleaſures and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,</hi> and ſought every thing that ſhould pleaſe his <hi>carnall eye,</hi> and <hi>tickle</hi> his <hi>vaine fancy;</hi> but he no ſooner <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but hee ſayes <hi>of mirth it is madneſſe, and of laughter what doth it?</hi> Chriſtians you muſt forget theſe, or Chriſt will <hi>overlook you. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> call'd the <hi>unvailed virgins</hi> of <note place="margin">Tetull. in lib. de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginibus.</note> his time <hi>Capita Nundinalitia,</hi> and <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor oſtentatitiae Virginitatis,</hi> Phraſes I will not Engliſh. You muſt forget
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199320:24"/> the <hi>pleaſures and vanities</hi> of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe: that is the fourth. I will inſtance but in one thing more.</p>
            <p>Fiftly and laſtly, <hi>You muſt forget the Religion and Righteouſneſſe of your fathers houſe.</hi> Indeed, there is not much there, it may quickly bee all <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten;</hi> but what there is muſt all bee <hi>forgotten.</hi> There is a <hi>conceited Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> at leaſt, a <hi>ſelfe-righteouſneſſe,</hi> which is <hi>naturall</hi> to all the <hi>ſons of Adam.</hi> Maſter <hi>Hooker</hi> gives this reaſon for it, becauſe our firſt father <hi>Adam</hi> was <hi>worth</hi> ſo much hee could have gone to Heaven upon his own <hi>legs.</hi> Now as it is with a young <hi>ſpenthrift,</hi> though hee hath ſpent all his <hi>fathers</hi> eſtate, and be not worth <hi>a groat,</hi> yet hee cannot <hi>abide</hi> to think hee ſhould bee a <hi>worſe man</hi> than his <hi>father;</hi> ſo it is with <hi>the ſons of Adam,</hi> becauſe hee could once have <hi>done enough</hi> for <hi>heaven,</hi> wee that are his <hi>children,</hi> though he loſt all his <hi>power</hi> before hee died, yet we cannot <hi>endure to think</hi> our ſelves <hi>worſe</hi> than our <hi>father,</hi> and are ready to think <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven may be erned</hi> ſtill, and we may doe ſomething for our ſelves. The <hi>young</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:199320:24"/> 
               <hi>man,</hi> Mat. 19. was at it, <hi>Maſter, what good thing ſhould I doe to inherit ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life?</hi> and ſo the converts at <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. and the Jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. <hi>What ſhall we doe to bee ſaved?</hi> hence is Morality and Civility taken up by ſome, and formality in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties taken up by others, and man <hi>pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth his ſtaffe</hi> in himſelfe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves there to <hi>reſt;</hi> but this muſt bee forgotten if ever we would be <hi>deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beautifull in Jeſus Chriſts eyes;</hi> for all our <hi>Righteouſneſſes are as menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous clothes, and as a filthie ragge in the ſight of God,</hi> Iſ. 64. 6. and againe, Matth. 5. 20. <hi>Except your righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees you ſhall never enter into the Kingdom of God. Civility</hi> reſted in (ſaith a Divine of our owne) is but <hi>a beautifull abomination,</hi> it is but a <hi>ſmooth way to hell.</hi> It is true, in the world <hi>a civill man</hi> is valued at an high rate, becauſe the world is full of <hi>groſſe profaneneſſe,</hi> and outrageous wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but <hi>Civility</hi> is like the <hi>Cab of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 6. 25</note> 
               <hi>Doves dung,</hi> or <hi>the aſſes head:</hi> the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was worth <hi>fourſcore pieces of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:199320:25"/> and the fourth part of the firſt valued at <hi>five pieces of ſilver;</hi> but it was becauſe there was a <hi>famine in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria.</hi> This is that makes <hi>Civility</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo <hi>high</hi> in the <hi>world,</hi> but in it ſelfe it is worth <hi>nothing,</hi> and <hi>Formality</hi> in <hi>duties</hi> as <hi>little,</hi> though it amounts to as much as the Phariſees <hi>faſting twice a week,</hi> and <hi>praying thrice a day,</hi> and <hi>pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tythe of all that hee hath.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, all <hi>God, I thank thee, I am not, &amp;c.</hi> yet the poor wretch is <hi>poore,</hi> and <hi>miſerable,</hi> and <hi>blind,</hi> and <hi>naked.</hi> All this muſt bee <hi>left,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> ſought and found, before the ſoule comes up to a <hi>deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beauty.</hi> And thus I have ſhewed what of our fathers houſe, and our own people muſt be forgot.</p>
            <p>Let me come in the next place, to ſhew you how, and how farre theſe things muſt be <hi>left</hi> and <hi>forgot;</hi> To that I anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Some of theſe muſt be abſolutely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got.</hi> The <hi>manners</hi> of our <hi>fathers houſe,</hi> all <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> muſt be ſo <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, Iſ.</hi> 55. 7. <hi>Let the wicked man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his way, and the unrighteous man</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:199320:25"/> 
               <hi>his thoughts,</hi> Hoſ. 14. 8. <hi>Ephraim ſhall ſay, what have I to do with Idols.</hi> There muſt bee no willing purpoſed <hi>practice</hi> of any ſinne how dear ſoever, how <hi>accuſtomed</hi> ſoever, however <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired,</hi> how long ſoever <hi>lived in;</hi> the wicked man muſt <hi>forſake his way,</hi> the <hi>evill of our doings</hi> muſt be <hi>put away;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill muſt bee <hi>eſchewed,</hi> ſo muſt ſinfull company too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The reſt of them muſt bee <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum quid</hi> forgotten, in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Our relations muſt not be <hi>doted upon,</hi> our honours and worldly glory not <hi>hunted after,</hi> nor muſt our hearts be <hi>taken with them;</hi> wee muſt not be <hi>lovers of pleaſure,</hi> wee muſt not <hi>reſt</hi> in our <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> not <hi>dote</hi> upon it; our heat of <hi>affection</hi> to theſe things, the <hi>running</hi> out of our hearts to them, the <hi>fixing</hi> of our hearts upon them, this muſt be <hi>forgotten,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Conditionally</hi> they muſt bee <hi>forgotten.</hi> If they <hi>claſh</hi> with Chriſts <hi>commands,</hi> if our <hi>Relations</hi> would <hi>draw us from Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>retard</hi> our <hi>way</hi> to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> if in our <hi>acts of love</hi> to them we muſt <hi>forget</hi> the <hi>commands</hi> of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199320:26"/> Chriſt, that either wee muſt not <hi>obey God</hi> in our places, or wee muſt <hi>break with them,</hi> and not be thought to <hi>love them,</hi> in this ſenſe they ought to bee <hi>forgotten,</hi> yea, to bee <hi>hated.</hi> Chriſt in this caſe call'd Peter <hi>Sathan;</hi> this is Chriſts command, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 26. If our <hi>honours</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> in the world would lie in the way, to keep us from <hi>ſtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to Chriſts command;</hi> and from thence our fleſh it would fetch ſuch <hi>concluſions</hi> as theſe, <hi>It is not fit for ſo great a perſon as you to have ſuch ſtrictneſſe in duties,</hi> to be <hi>acquainted with ſuch meane creatures</hi> (as many <hi>Saints</hi> are) to go <hi>to Church ſo often,</hi> to be at <hi>private meetingt ſo much, &amp;c.</hi> In this caſe we muſt forget them. If our riches begin to <hi>ſtick to our heart,</hi> and to <hi>tempt our heart from God,</hi> that wee cannot <hi>enjoy them,</hi> but our hearts will <hi>cleave to them,</hi> In ſuch a caſe a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhall bee a <hi>ſaver,</hi> if (as <hi>Crates</hi> threw his <hi>gold</hi> into <hi>ſea,</hi> that hee may ſtudy <hi>Philoſophy)</hi> hee alſo <hi>throw</hi> away his <hi>eſtate</hi> to <hi>ſtudy Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> If our <hi>pleaſures</hi> be ſuch, as in the <hi>ſubstance</hi> (if ſuch <hi>ſhadowes</hi> have any) are ſinfull,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:199320:26"/> or <hi>draw away</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> too much <hi>from God,</hi> take up our <hi>Church-time,</hi> or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily <hi>duty-time,</hi> or ſecret <hi>duty-time, &amp;c.</hi> in ſuch caſe they muſt bee forgot too.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Comparatively they muſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got.</hi> God muſt be greater than they <hi>in the throne of our heart,</hi> wee muſt not <hi>love father, nor mother, nor daughter, nor wife, nor child, more than Chriſt.</hi> So <hi>Mathew</hi> expounds that place, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 26. in <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 37. wee muſt not be <hi>lovers of any pleaſures more than of Chriſt,</hi> nor of <hi>houſe, or lands, or honour, or any piece of vanity under the Sunne.</hi> This is plaine, for we muſt <hi>love Chriſt</hi> with <hi>all our heart</hi> and <hi>ſoule;</hi> and though the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment bee, <hi>thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe,</hi> yet it doth not ſay, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, <hi>In effect they muſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got.</hi> Chriſtians muſt <hi>doe</hi> as if they had no <hi>relations;</hi> they may <hi>rejoyce,</hi> and <hi>buy, and ſell,</hi> and <hi>purchaſe,</hi> and <hi>uſe the world,</hi> but marke how, it is in a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting</hi> manner, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 30. <hi>they that</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:199320:27"/> 
               <hi>rejoyce muſt be as if they rejoyced not, and they that buy as if they poſſeſt not, and they that uſe the world as if they uſed it not.</hi> Chriſtians may be called by their titles of <hi>Rabbi,</hi> and <hi>my Lord,</hi> and <hi>Madam;</hi> but while they are ſo, they muſt have a <hi>ſcornfull, low, ſlight, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme</hi> of theſe <hi>ſwelling words of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> not deſpiſing the meaneſt of Gods <hi>Saints,</hi> but ready in <hi>honour</hi> to <hi>preferre them above themſelves,</hi> and <hi>accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> the title of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> of a <hi>ſervant</hi> of God, to be a <hi>greater title of honour</hi> than worldly <hi>dignities can inveſt them with.</hi> And now I have finiſhed my firſt taske in the explication of the doctrine, in which I have ſhewed you, <hi>what of our fathers houſe muſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</hi> 2. <hi>How farre we muſt forget it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I propounded, was to ſhew you how that ſoule is beautifull, with what beauty the ſoule is beautifull that thus <hi>forgets its owne people,</hi> and its <hi>fathers houſe.</hi> This I ſhall ſhew you, 1. <hi>Negatively.</hi> 2. <hi>Poſitively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Not <hi>with a corporall beauty,</hi> this makes not the fleſh beautifull. It ads no <hi>luſtre</hi> to <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> poſſibly it may <hi>diſcolour</hi> that.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:199320:27"/> 2. Not <hi>by a native beauty, no natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall beauty.</hi> The <hi>beauty</hi> that will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the ſoule, upon this ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, is not like the <hi>beauty</hi> of the <hi>face</hi> which appears after <hi>waſhing off dirt,</hi> which clouded natures colours.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Not <hi>in the eye of the vaine crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor in its owne eyes.</hi> Aske a vaine creature, he will tell you, that the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of <hi>vaine dreſſes,</hi> and <hi>patches,</hi> and <hi>plaitinge</hi> of the <hi>haire,</hi> is the way to make the creature look <hi>like no body,</hi> to make it <hi>deſpiſed in the world, &amp;c.</hi> and ſuch a one perhaps <hi>lothes and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors it ſelfe</hi> as a vile creature, <hi>Jo.</hi> 42. 6. Thus it ſhall not be beautifull, and it is no matter whether it be or no. But ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly ſuch a ſoule ſhall bee <hi>beautifull</hi> theſe three wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Imputatione,</hi> By the <hi>beauty</hi> of Chriſt put upon it; ſee for this that notable place, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16. 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>Then waſt thou decked with ſilver and gold, and thy rayment was of fine linnen, and ſilke, and broide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red worke.—and thou wert excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding beautifull.—And thy renowne went forth amongſt the heathen for thy</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:199320:28"/> 
               <hi>beauty, for it was perfect through the comelineſſe which I had put uppon thee (ſaith the Lord God.)</hi> Chriſt makes the <hi>reflexion</hi> of his <hi>beauty</hi> to bee <hi>caſt upon ſuch a ſoule,</hi> and it becomes <hi>beautifull</hi> through his <hi>comelineſſe;</hi> the <hi>ſoules doing theſe things,</hi> doth not make it <hi>ſpiritually</hi> any more than <hi>corporally beautifull,</hi> but (they being done) it <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes comely</hi> through <hi>Chriſts comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> comely through a <hi>comelineſſe</hi> that is <hi>put upon it, that's</hi> the firſt way. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, It is <hi>beautifull,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Through <hi>Chriſts Aceeptation, Of free grace;</hi> Chriſt ſaid to the young man in the 19 of Matth. <hi>Sell all thou haſt, &amp;c.</hi> and thou <hi>ſhalt have treaſure in heaven,</hi> not thou ſhalt <hi>earne</hi> it, but thou ſhalt <hi>have</hi> it. Chriſt <hi>accepts</hi> the ſoule as <hi>beautifull,</hi> and <hi>accounts</hi> the ſoule as <hi>beautifull,</hi> that <hi>for his ſake</hi> will <hi>forget its owne people,</hi> and its fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Behold, thou art faire (my love) behold, thou art faire, thou haſt doves eyes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Such a ſoule is beautifull, though not in the worlds eyes, yet in the Saints eyes;</hi> The world will <hi>hate</hi> and <hi>deſpiſe</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:199320:28"/> 
               <hi>them,</hi> but the Saints will <hi>love</hi> and <hi>value them, Cant.</hi> 6. 1. the Daughters of Hieruſalem ſay unto the ſpouſe, <hi>whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is thy beloved gone, O thou Faireſt amongſt women,</hi> the daughters of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> the Saints, account ſuch a ſoule <hi>beautifull.</hi> It may bee that ſhee may call her ſelfe <hi>black,</hi> the <hi>greateſt of ſinners,</hi> and the <hi>leaſt of Saints,</hi> yea, and the <hi>world</hi> may ſo call her; but thoſe that are <hi>godly</hi> ſhall eſteeme her <hi>comely,</hi> and <hi>the King ſhall deſire her beauty.</hi> And that leads me to the laſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar in the explication of the Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What is the meaning of that phraſe, <hi>The King ſhall deſire thy beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Generally.</hi> It is a ſpeech accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the manner of men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 7. it is ſaid of the husband toward the wiſe, <hi>Vnto thee ſhall be his deſire.</hi> And wee meet with that phraſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 11. <hi>when thou ſeeſt amongſt the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives a beautifull woman, and thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſhall be towards her, to make her thy wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But more particularly, I think the true meaning of the phraſe may bee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199320:29"/> underſtood in theſe <hi>particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of all it implies, <hi>That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhall diſcover and ſee an excellency in ſuch a ſoule;</hi> we can <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing,</hi> but we ſhall firſt diſcover ſome <hi>excellency in it.</hi> Now the Lord diſcovers an <hi>excellency</hi> in ſuch a ſoule; hee ſhall eye ſuch a ſoule as an <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> ſoule, as a <hi>lovely ſoule,</hi> worthy of him (though not through its owne <hi>worthineſſe)</hi> and <hi>ſuitable</hi> for him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It implies, <hi>That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhall love ſuch a ſoule,</hi> diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in it a <hi>ſuitable excellency;</hi> he ſhall love it, his heart will be <hi>raviſhed</hi> with it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. 9. <hi>Thou haſt raviſhed my heart, my ſiſter, my ſpouſe, thou haſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed my heart.</hi> Chriſts <hi>affections</hi> will be drawne out to a ſoule that ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets it ſelfe, his <hi>heart</hi> will bee <hi>melting</hi> towards it, and <hi>on fire</hi> for it; there muſt firſt bee a <hi>love in the ſoule</hi> to the <hi>object,</hi> before the heart bee drawne forth to covet an <hi>union</hi> with it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It implies, <hi>That the Lord Chriſt will in his heart preferre ſuch a ſoule;</hi> when a mans <hi>deſire</hi> is towards a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular woman,</hi> to make her his wife, he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:199320:29"/> 
               <hi>preferres</hi> her above other <hi>women;</hi> his deſire is <hi>not to her ſex,</hi> but <hi>to her,</hi> to her rather than <hi>ten thouſand</hi> others. The Lords <hi>deſire ſhall bee towards ſuch a ſoule,</hi> As you have heard deſcribed to you, that hee will <hi>preferre her</hi> above <hi>ten thouſand</hi> of his creatures, though the Lord ſees <hi>thouſands of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> hundreds in a congregation, that <hi>the world dotes</hi> upon, ſome for their <hi>faire faces,</hi> and on others for their <hi>brave parts,</hi> this <hi>Eliab</hi> and the other <hi>Shammah;</hi> yet the Lord that <hi>ſees all,</hi> and can <hi>judge beſt,</hi> lets <hi>Eliab</hi> and <hi>Shammah</hi> paſſe, and <hi>fixeth his eye</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this <hi>ſelfe denying</hi> (in the world) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed <hi>creature,</hi> and upon it hee <hi>fixeth his</hi> heart, and <hi>prizeth</hi> ſuch a ſoule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the other <hi>trumperies</hi> and <hi>kick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhawes</hi> of beauty. The Lord culs out ſuch a ſoule, his <hi>deſire</hi> is towards her, ſhee is the <hi>Eſther</hi> hee picks out, and ſuch a ſoul is more <hi>preferred</hi> in Chriſts <hi>eye,</hi> than this <hi>witty man</hi> or <hi>woman,</hi> or <hi>that gallant,</hi> this <hi>Lord</hi> or that <hi>Lady,</hi> Chriſt hath <hi>no deſire</hi> to them, but to this ſoule his <hi>deſire</hi> is.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It implies, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt will</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:199320:30"/> 
               <hi>indeavour and effect an union, and enjoy ſuch a ſoule;</hi> what is the meaning of that phraſe, <hi>the man's deſire ſhall be to his wife,</hi> but he ſhall deſire to <hi>be joyned in marriage to her,</hi> that they may bee <hi>no longer twaine, but one fleſh?</hi> and if his deſire be towards her, and it be a <hi>feaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> thing he will effect it, if <hi>ſhee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> and friends conſent, &amp;c. <hi>The Lords deſire ſhall be to the ſoule,</hi> that is, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhall indeavour, yea, and unite himſelfe to effect an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with ſuch a ſoul, he ſhall wooe it, yea, and ſhee ſhall <hi>yield,</hi> for when hee <hi>works who can let him?</hi> Chriſt will marry himſelfe to ſuch a ſoule, make a marriage <hi>covenant,</hi> and <hi>tie himſelfe</hi> in a <hi>marriage</hi> bond to it; for though in man deſire may bee fruſtrated, ſo that deſire and enjoyment are two things, yet it is neceſſarily to be underſtood in <hi>Chriſts deſiring,</hi> whoſe power is ſuch, that hee ſhall not need ſtarve his deſire longer than he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It implies, That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt will court neare communion with ſuch a ſoule; mark how he ſpeaks to the Spouſe, Cant, 2. 14. <hi>O my</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:199320:30"/> 
               <hi>Dove, that art in the clefts of the rocks, in the ſecret places of the ſtaires, let me heare thy voice, for ſweet is thy voice, and thy countenance comely;</hi> hee will not onely have communion, but hee will <hi>covet</hi> communion with ſuch a ſoule; hee will deſire to have it <hi>draw nigh,</hi> and <hi>dwell</hi> in his <hi>preſence,</hi> to have it come neare him in a duty, in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, <hi>Hee will love ſuch a ſoule with a conſtant and inſeparable love,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>The King ſhall deſire thy beauty,</hi> he ſhall deſire it, and never ceaſe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it, hee ſhall for ever <hi>deſire thy beauty.</hi> And thus I have opened to you all the three termes, now I come to the ſecond taske. As I have gone along in opening the generals in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall particulars, I have proved the Doctrine that it is ſo. But may ſome ſay, what ground is there that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhould deſire this of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule that hee will <hi>love and marry</hi> and have <hi>communion</hi> with, that it ſhould thus forſake <hi>its owne people,</hi> and its <hi>fathers houſe?</hi> why ſhould Chriſt hold the ſoule to this hard meat? I ſhal
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199320:31"/> therefore in the next place ſhew you the reaſons of it: And there is a very great deale of Reaſon for it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe it is the very law of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> Gen. 2. 24. <hi>Therefore ſhall a man forſake father and mother, and cleave to his wife.</hi> The Lord Chriſt marries himſelfe to the ſoule. It is written, <hi>I will betroth thee unto mee; yea, I will betroth thee unto mee:</hi> for this cauſe the ſoule ſhall forſake its owne people, and its fathers houſe, and ſhall cleave to its Chriſt; <hi>for this cauſe</hi> becauſe the ſoule is <hi>married,</hi> or <hi>about to marry</hi> to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and therefore muſt look to doe as mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried perſons uſe to doe, leave all for their husband.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond reaſon is, <hi>becauſe while the ſoule lives at home with its owne people, and at its fathers houſe, it cannot be beautifull nor deſirable.</hi> Our owne people are a <hi>filthie people,</hi> our <hi>fathers houſe</hi> a naſtie houſe; the ſoule while it hath left that cannot be <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull</hi> nor <hi>deſirable.</hi> The moſt <hi>beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full creature</hi> you know, if ſhee bee brought up by ſluttiſh people (as wee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199320:31"/> ſay) and goes in a <hi>filthy habit,</hi> there is a <hi>cloud</hi> caſt over her <hi>beauty.</hi> So it is with a ſoule, while it hath left its <hi>ſins and vaine company,</hi> and <hi>pride,</hi> and <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,</hi> and <hi>pleaſures,</hi> and <hi>riches,</hi> and <hi>ſelfe-righteouſneſſe,</hi> it cannot be <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in Chriſts eyes.</hi> Now beauty is the <hi>attractive</hi> of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> the ſoule muſt ſee a <hi>beauty,</hi> in that, which it <hi>lets out it ſelfe</hi> to in <hi>deſiring:</hi> let that be a ſecond reaſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe <hi>there cannot bee a clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to Chriſt, unleſſe there be a parting with theſe.</hi> Chriſt requires the <hi>higheſt love</hi> of our ſoules, it is the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement you know (with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours gloſſe upon it) <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and all thy ſoule.</hi> Hence Chriſt tels us, <hi>no man can ſerve two maſters, you cannot ſerve God and Mammon;</hi> that ſoule that will <hi>hug ſin</hi> muſt <hi>hate God;</hi> that ſoule that will be a <hi>companion of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and a <hi>companion of Saints,</hi> muſt not be a <hi>companion of ſinners, for what fellowſhip hath Chriſt with Belial, righteouſneſſe with unrighteouſneſſe, light with darkneſſe, the temple of God</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:199320:32"/> 
               <hi>with Idols,</hi> and ſo the reſt? <hi>Your ſoule cannot love two thengs with an higheſt</hi> love. 2. You <hi>cannot in heart truly cleave to two contraries.</hi> There is a third reaſon, eſpecially if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That God is a jealous God:</hi> you meet with the phraſe often, and given as a reaſon, why they ſhould doe this or that, <hi>For the Lord thy God is a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God. Jealouſie</hi> is a <hi>paſſion in the</hi> ſoule, <hi>non patiens conſortium in re ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tà</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aquinas)</hi> that will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, or that makes the ſoule that it will not indure any <hi>ſharing in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject beloved.</hi> The woman that hath a <hi>jealous husband</hi> muſt leave all her <hi>old companions.</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>thy God is a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God,</hi> if therefore thou wouldſt have him <hi>deſire thy beauty,</hi> if thou wouldſt have him <hi>care for thee,</hi> thou muſt <hi>forget thine owne people,</hi> and thy <hi>fathers houſe.</hi> I will adde but one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon more. Laſtly,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe <hi>It is the will of Chriſt.</hi> It was the Apoſtles precept, that <hi>wives</hi> ſhould <hi>obey their husbands.</hi> Now <hi>ſelfe deniall</hi> is a great piece of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199320:32"/> It is his firſt requeſt, <hi>Hee that will be my Diſciple let him deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe;</hi> ſelfe deniall is the firſt of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</hi> He that hath not learned this, hath not learned the <hi>A, B, C,</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, not ſo much as the <hi>Chriſt-croſſe row,</hi> as you call it. Here ſhould bee reaſon enough if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, [hee hath ſaid ſo] was enough in <hi>Pithago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> his ſchoole, to put the <hi>buſineſſe</hi> paſt <hi>diſputing</hi> amongſt his <hi>ſchollers,</hi> I am ſure it ſhould bee much more in <hi>Chriſts ſchoole,</hi> wee will therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire no further reaſon for it. Let mee now come to application.</p>
            <p>I ſhall apply it, by way 1. Of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. 2. Of Examination. 3. Of Conſolation. 4. Of Exhortation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> 
               <label>Inſtr.</label> It may ſerve to inſtruct us in the truth of ſeverall Poſitions, I will only pick out ſome few.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It may inſtruct us, <hi>That the moſt part of the world, yea, of thoſe that the world moſt eſteemes of, and ſets the higheſt rate and value upon, are poore, indeſirable, uncomely wretches, in the eyes of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Chriſt's eye <hi>ſees not as mans eye ſeeth,</hi> man ſeeth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199320:33"/> 
               <hi>beauty,</hi> where Chriſt <hi>ſeeth none;</hi> man ſeeth a <hi>deſirableneſſe,</hi> where Chriſt's eye ſeeth none; man <hi>dotes</hi> upon what <hi>Chriſt cares not for;</hi> man calleth the <hi>proud bleſſed,</hi> but the Lord's ſoule <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth them;</hi> they have not yet left <hi>their owne people, and their fathers houſe.</hi> You ſee many a <hi>gallant ſtrut</hi> it in the <hi>world,</hi> and who but they are the people of faſhion (as you call them) the <hi>glory,</hi> the <hi>beauty</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> every one admires them, &amp;c. many that in reſpect of their <hi>wiſdome,</hi> or <hi>parts,</hi> or <hi>behaviour,</hi> and <hi>civility,</hi> are the <hi>deſire of thoſe</hi> amongſt whom they <hi>live,</hi> and there is not one in ten of all theſe that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>hath any deſire too;</hi> they are <hi>poore, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely,</hi> indeſirable <hi>creatures in Chriſt's eyes,</hi> notwithſtanding all their <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> and <hi>nobility,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their <hi>beauty,</hi> whether <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall</hi> or <hi>artificiall,</hi> borrowed from the <hi>Painter</hi> or <hi>Taylor,</hi> notwithſtanding all theſe Chriſt ſeeth no <hi>excellency in them at all.</hi> The vaine creature <hi>dotes,</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſcornes;</hi> the vain creature <hi>loves,</hi> Chriſt ſees no <hi>lovelineſſe in them,</hi> but
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199320:33"/> looketh upon them <hi>black</hi> with the <hi>ſoot of hell,</hi> eyes their countenance, all <hi>blots,</hi> and their <hi>ſoules</hi> too, the vaine creature <hi>preferres</hi> them: there's many a poore creature that lives in a <hi>cottage,</hi> that is at an higher rate in <hi>Chriſt's</hi> thoughts; the poore wormes ſoule is carried out to deſire <hi>matches,</hi> an <hi>union</hi> and a <hi>communion.</hi> with them. Jeſus Chriſt <hi>ſcornes them,</hi> and hath no <hi>deſire either to any union, or to enjoy any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with them: Chriſt ſaith of ſuch vaine creatures, There go poor wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that <hi>my ſoule loathes,</hi> I am ſick of them, <hi>aſhamed</hi> of them as my <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;</hi> And is this nothing to you? O you <hi>ſons</hi> and <hi>daughters,</hi> is this nothing to you? it vexeth you to think that you live in a place where none <hi>deſires</hi> you, and if you were gone none would <hi>lament</hi> you: It was an untoward cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of an unworthy <hi>Emperour;</hi> &amp; is it no trouble to you to think I live not deſired, not cared for of Jeſus Chriſt? <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2. 1. The Lord cals his people to repentance under this notion; Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together, <hi>O nation not deſired.</hi> O that it might call you to ſome ſerious
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199320:34"/> thoughts, vaine creatures! you are people not <hi>deſired</hi> of the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>uncomely,</hi> and <hi>deſpiſed</hi> in his eyes, as you are <hi>beautifull,</hi> and <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> in the <hi>eyes</hi> of men; nay, and more, and let me tell you in your eares, and (oh that it may make your hearts rend, and your eares tingle) if you be not <hi>deſired of him here,</hi> you ſhall never <hi>enjoy him, nor be enjoyed of him bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi> Haman was ſuch a poore wretch, the King had <hi>ennobled</hi> him, every <hi>hat</hi> and <hi>knee</hi> did him <hi>homage,</hi> and took notice of the Kings <hi>reſpects</hi> to him, at laſt hee came to the <hi>gibbet;</hi> have a care poore creatures elſe, <hi>though you compaſſe your ſelves about with ſparkes,</hi> poore ſparkes of <hi>friends, honours, riches, pleaſures;</hi> ſparks that will extinguiſh as quickly as riſe, yet <hi>this,</hi> and onely this, <hi>you ſhall have at the Lords hand, you ſhall lie downe in ſorrow,</hi> everlaſting ſorrow; you ſhall <hi>lie down in hell.</hi> It is an ill place to leave you in, but the Lord pluck you as fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands out of the burning. I paſſe on.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From what you have heard you may be inſtructed, <hi>which way the way</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:199320:34"/> 
               <hi>to heaven lies;</hi> and 2. <hi>That it is no eaſie way,</hi> we are all <hi>pilgrims</hi> and <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> here, we were bred ſo, our fathers were ſo. Now the journies end which all pretend to (though the moſt ride backward) the coaſt which all ſay they are bound for (which way ſoever their compaſſe guides them) is <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> this is <hi>omnibus in Voto,</hi> though few <hi>ſo runne that they may obtaine.</hi> But hath any blind or miſled traveller a mind to know the way? Is any poore ſoule ſtartled this day? doth hell-fire flaſh in any of your faces, and are you crying out, Sir, <hi>What ſhall we doe to be ſaved? which way lies our way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi> Learne hence, that the next way to heaven is not the <hi>beaten road,</hi> but quite croſſe <hi>Natures-fields,</hi> and ſo through the <hi>long ſtreet of ſelfe-deniall,</hi> and up the <hi>mountaine of holineſſe,</hi> at the top of which <hi>you ſhall ſee God;</hi> it lies over <hi>hedge</hi> and <hi>ditch,</hi> over <hi>rockes</hi> and <hi>mountaines:</hi> you muſt leave your <hi>youth ſinnes</hi> as you goe on your <hi>right hand,</hi> your <hi>education</hi> and <hi>cuſtome ſinnes</hi> on your <hi>left hand,</hi> your <hi>beloved ſinnes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind you; if your father, or mother,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199320:35"/> or husband, or wife, or brother, or ſiſter, or child lie in your way, you muſt make no halts, but over their necks; if all your vaine acquaintance, your drunken, ſwearing, wanton compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ſtand of each ſide and becken you another way, you muſt decline their invitation and go quite croſſe; you muſt tread upon all your <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>pompe,</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe;</hi> you muſt avoid the <hi>mountaine of Gold,</hi> and the <hi>rocks of Pearle;</hi> you muſt take heed of the pleaſant <hi>brook of carnall and vain plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures;</hi> avoid your <hi>dancing,</hi> and <hi>pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> and <hi>patching,</hi> and <hi>decking your ſelves:</hi> In ſhort, you muſt put your ſelfe in an <hi>habit fit to carry a croſſe,</hi> This is the next way to heaven. And now I need not tell you in the ſecond place, <hi>That ſtrait is the way, and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is the gate that leads to everlaſting life, and few there be that find it.</hi> By this time you will know, that if you will goe to heaven you muſt goe <hi>like,</hi> and <hi>with,</hi> very <hi>few</hi> in this age of <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe and dotage.</hi> By this time you will eaſily gheſſe ſinners are out of the way, and proud men are out of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199320:35"/> way; thoſe that <hi>glory</hi> in riches, and <hi>worldly greatneſſe,</hi> are out of the way; the <hi>careleſſe daughters</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> that <hi>ſtretch out their necks, and mince it as they goe,</hi> are out of the way; the <hi>ſelfe-righteous men are out of the way.</hi> Ah Lord! who are in it? Heaven is a <hi>difficult journey,</hi> it is an hard way to find, it is hard to fleſh and blood to doe theſe things. It was the Martyrs ſpeech, that <hi>the croſſe way was the way to heaven.</hi> The way to heaven is aſtrait way, no dancing way, dancers muſt have the elbowroome of hell-road; they that will walke in this ſtrait way muſt <hi>croud,</hi> they muſt not thinke to walk thither in ſtate; no, they muſt croud, and never bee afraid of wrim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling a neat <hi>handkerchiefe or cuffe,</hi> it is not <hi>opus pulvinaris</hi> (ſaid one) but <hi>pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veris,</hi> you ſhall be ſure to meet with all the <hi>oppoſition</hi> that nature can make, all the forces of <hi>fleſh and bloud,</hi> and all the forces the <hi>devill</hi> can adde; <hi>who then ſhall be ſaved?</hi> even thoſe that God hath appointed to life, thoſe to whom the Lord ſhall give ſuch an heart as I have told you, <hi>ſtrait is the way, and few there be that find:</hi> If you will have
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199320:36"/> a broader way you may, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 13, 14. but then you muſt not look for the ſame journies end. The Lord give you hearts to <hi>conſider it,</hi> and feare to tremble at it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And from hence thirdly, you may bee inſtructed, <hi>that it muſt bee ſomething more than nature that muſt make a poore ſoule beautifull, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably beautifull in Jeſus Chriſts eyes.</hi> It muſt neither bee <hi>naturall beauty</hi> will doe it, nor yet <hi>naturall parts;</hi> no, nor <hi>natures glory,</hi> nor the beſt of <hi>nature, naturall righteouſneſſe, Matth.</hi> 5. 20. It muſt be ſomething more than <hi>fleſh and bloud,</hi> yea, ſomething more than <hi>fleſh and bloud</hi> can helpe us with. But I paſſe over this.</p>
            <p n="4">4. From hence fourthly, you may be inſtructed, <hi>What an infinit love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath loved his Saints with,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 1. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>with what manner of love the father hath loved you with, that you ſhould be call'd the ſonnes of God.</hi> Here hee ſayes, <hi>hearken O Daughter;</hi> the Daughter of a <hi>King</hi> is honourable, but the daughter of <hi>the King of Kings</hi> is much more honourable. But (if I may
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199320:36"/> ſay it) here ſeemes to be a degree of <hi>love</hi> beyond it, the <hi>Kings wife</hi> is more honourable than the <hi>Kings daughter.</hi> Behold therefore (O yee upright in heart) with what manner of love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath loved you, that hee ſhould <hi>deſire your beauty;</hi> not only love you, but if uncomely, poor wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, make you beautifull, according to that, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16. 13, 14. nay, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but <hi>deſire your beauty;</hi> not onely like it, but deſire it; O love! infinit love! when <hi>David</hi> ſent his ſervants to let <hi>Abigail</hi> know that hee deſired her beauty, marke how ſhe admires at it, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 41. <hi>ſhee aroſe and bowed her ſelfe on the earth, and ſaid, Behold, let thine handmaid bee a ſervant, to waſh the feet of the ſervants of my Lord,</hi> Doe you heare this newes, O yee daughters of men? doe you heare this newes? that the King of glory, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that hath no need of you, that is infinitly above you, hath ſent me this day to tell you, that hee <hi>deſires your beauty.</hi> Riſe up, O yee Saints, bow your ſelves, and ſay, <hi>Let us be ſervants to waſh his feet, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:199320:37"/> Let us bee the <hi>doore-keepers</hi> of his houſe, his meaneſt ſervants. No Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, you ſhall be his <hi>ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:</hi> Nay, hearken O <hi>daughters,</hi> here's more for you, The King <hi>deſires your beauty;</hi> Spell this love at leiſure, and now <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh your ſoules, follow</hi> after Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, ſtudy it with your moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thoughts, live to it with ſtricteſt lives. What converſation becommeth the goſpell? what manner of perſons ſhould you be? <hi>Follow</hi> on, <hi>make haſte</hi> and <hi>riſe,</hi> and <hi>follow</hi> him, ſinging, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as you goe, <hi>O the heighth, and depth,</hi> the <hi>incomprehenſible heighth!</hi> the <hi>unfadomable</hi> depth of love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath loved ſinners, before the beginning of the world, &amp;c. And laſtly.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Can you learn a leſſe reſult from hence than this, that <hi>Saints ſelfe-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, deſpiſed</hi> Saints, <hi>are happy creatures; Ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quater<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> beati,</hi> bleſſed againe, and againe. Surely you have not heard mee all this while, but you are preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me in the words of the Pſalmiſt. <hi>Happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe; yea, bleſſed are the people that</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:199320:37"/> 
               <hi>have the Lord for their God;</hi> we may ſay of them, <hi>O nimium dilectis Deo,</hi> creatures ſtrangely beloved of their God, ſtrangely happy in this, that the King ſhould deſire their beauty. Let the world <hi>ſcorne</hi> one, let them <hi>put out the finger</hi> and <hi>barke at the moone,</hi> let them mock <hi>puritaniſme,</hi> let the <hi>way of holineſſe</hi> be <hi>every where ſpoken againſt, pro hominum arbitrio,</hi> let them talke, ſo long as you <hi>gaine;</hi> you <hi>dance before the ark</hi> though <hi>Michal mock out at the window:</hi> You ſhall be <hi>more beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> the more vile they think you; it is for the Kings ſake, that <hi>hath deſired your beauty</hi> and <hi>ſcornd</hi> theirs; for the Kings ſake, that hath choſen you to <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine everlaſting life through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> but hath <hi>ordained them to wrath,</hi> and <hi>neglected their beauty.</hi> One would not think now, that theſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that <hi>raviſh Chriſts heart,</hi> ſhould <hi>offend worldlings eyes</hi> ſo much: ſurely Chriſt ſhould have no judgement, if theſe were the contemptible ones of the earth, the <hi>unlovely</hi> creatures. Well well, Chriſtians, let them mocke on, after the way which they call <hi>ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:199320:38"/> 
               <hi>and foolery, moping; &amp;c. worſhip thou the God of thy fathers;</hi> thou ſhalt have thy <hi>pleaſures,</hi> when they ſhall have <hi>torments;</hi> thou ſhalt have thy <hi>crowne</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> when the <hi>pride of their glory ſhall bee ſtained,</hi> and that ſhall lie in the duſt. Theſe <hi>children of vanity</hi> forget what <hi>Abraham</hi> (though ſomething too late to doe him good) adviſed their <hi>brother</hi> to remember, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 25. <hi>That in their life time they received good things,</hi> and thoſe precious <hi>Lazarus'es, evill things,</hi> but yet a little while and you ſhall be <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted,</hi> and they <hi>tormented;</hi> yet a little while and you ſhall be <hi>honoured,</hi> and they ſhall be <hi>curſing the wombe that bare them, and the paps that gave them ſuck,</hi> curſing the <hi>honour that ruin'd them,</hi> the <hi>pleaſures</hi> that <hi>damned them,</hi> the <hi>worldly glory</hi> which hath made them <hi>inglorious for ever;</hi> yet a little while and inſtead of their <hi>ſweet ſmels</hi> they ſhall have the <hi>ſtinkes of fire and brimſtone,</hi> and inſtead of their <hi>girdles rentings</hi> of heart for ever, inſtead of their <hi>well-ſet haire</hi> they ſhall have <hi>baldneſſe;</hi> they ſhall ſpend more time
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:199320:38"/> in <hi>rending and tearing their haire,</hi> than ever they did in <hi>curling or powdring it.</hi> Yet a little while, and inſtead of their <hi>ſtomachers,</hi> they ſhall have <hi>girdings with ſackcloth,</hi> &amp; <hi>everlaſting burnings</hi> inſtead of their <hi>preſent beauty.</hi> But bleſſed ſhall you bee, for <hi>you ſhall ſhine like the Sun in the firmament of the father,</hi> for <hi>the King hath deſired your beauty.</hi> I have at laſt done with my firſt uſe of Inſtruction: I proceed now to a ſecond, and that ſhall bee of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> Are you willing now to know, Chriſtians, whether Jeſus Chriſt cares for you yea or no? whether you be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable in his eyes yea or no? heaven and hell hang upon this thing; <hi>Trie whether you have forgotten your owne people, and your fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt men and women are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the <hi>touchſtone,</hi> and are willing rather to take <hi>heaven for granted,</hi> though they find <hi>hell for certaine;</hi> but this is not ſafe with you. Trie your ſelves then (Chriſtians) I will helpe you a little in ſo good a work.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you have forgotten your
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199320:39"/> fathers houſe, <hi>you have</hi> (firſt) <hi>ſeene a great deale of folly and vanity in it:</hi> Man is a reaſonable creature, and will never leave any thing, but he will ſee <hi>ſome cauſe to leave it.</hi> Did the Lord ever yet <hi>convince you</hi> throughly, not with a <hi>Notionall,</hi> but an <hi>heart convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of the <hi>folly</hi> of your <hi>fathers houſe?</hi> Did the Lord ever <hi>throughly</hi> convince you of your <hi>evill wayes,</hi> the ſinnes of your natures, the <hi>cuſtomary ſinnes of your lives,</hi> of your <hi>education ſinnes,</hi> and your <hi>beloved ſinnes?</hi> Had you ever a <hi>through conviction</hi> of the vanity of your evill company, the vanity of your <hi>pleaſures</hi> and carnall <hi>delights?</hi> Did your ſoules ever taſt a reall bitterneſſe in them? if not, I feare me you have not left them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Have you had another excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy diſcovered to your ſoules?</hi> Had your ſouls ever yet a <hi>reall diſcovery made to you</hi> of the <hi>excellency of the wayes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines,</hi> theſe wayes that you once hated? Doe you now ſee a <hi>beauty,</hi> a <hi>glory</hi> in them, ſo much that you can even <hi>ſtand,</hi> and <hi>hold up your hands</hi> and <hi>admire,</hi> that you ſhould be <hi>blind</hi> ſo long? A
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:199320:39"/> preſent pleaſant thing will ſcarce bee left, but upon a <hi>diſcovery of,</hi> and an <hi>obtaining of</hi> ſomething <hi>more excellent.</hi> Chriſtians, under what notion do you look upon Chriſt, and his wayes? Do you look upon them as <hi>excellent,</hi> the wayes of <hi>ſtrictneſſe,</hi> as <hi>excellent, ſanctifying a Sabboth, praying,</hi> the <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting of the communion</hi> of <hi>Saints?</hi> Doe you look upon them as excellent? If you doe not, I feare mee, you but cheat your ſelves with a conceit, that you have forgot <hi>your fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>If you have parted with them I am afraid it coſt you ſome teares,</hi> you did not part with ſo many <hi>friends</hi> with <hi>drie eyes;</hi> friends cannot ordinarily <hi>pats</hi> without <hi>teares,</hi> but your weeping hath not beene ſuch a weeping if it hath been true; it hath not been, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have parted with them, but becauſe you abode with them ſo long; it hath for meaſure been like the <hi>mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of him that hath loſt his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne,</hi> Zach. 12. 10. but not upon the ſame <hi>account,</hi> not becauſe you muſt now <hi>part</hi> with them, but becauſe you <hi>embraced</hi> them ſo long. See the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:199320:40"/> effects of godly ſorrow, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11. it worketh <hi>carefulneſſe</hi> and <hi>indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. Were your ſoules ever in ſuch a true <hi>bitterneſſe for ſinne,</hi> that it wrought in thee an <hi>indignation</hi> againſt your ſelves; that you could even <hi>eat</hi> your owne fleſh, to think you ſhould ever have been ſuch <hi>a vaine, wanton wretch,</hi> ſuch a <hi>proud ſinner</hi> as you have been? This is a good ſigne you and your fathers houſe are parted, and that at the parting you ſorrowed after a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſort.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If ever you truly parted with it, <hi>both at the parting, and ſince too, you have found ſomething to doe with your owne ſpirit,</hi> ſome <hi>ſtruglings</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batings</hi> with your ſelfe. Before you parted you were at a <hi>diſpute</hi> with your <hi>ſoules;</hi> ſhall I leave this or that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, or ſhall I not? and ſince you have been at ſome debates with your ſpirit, ſhall I goe home againe? ſhall I returne to ſuch a vomit? to ſuch a wallowing in the mire? even <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe found <hi>the law in his members warring againſt the law of his mind, and bringing him into captivity to the law</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:199320:40"/> 
               <hi>of ſinne,</hi> Rom. 7. 23. <hi>the fleſh luſting againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, and theſe contrary one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Gal. 5. 17. I dare almoſt ſay, that that ſoule never <hi>conquerd ſinne,</hi> that is not yet <hi>in combate with it;</hi> never truly overcame it, that is not ſtill in <hi>combate;</hi> never yet <hi>forgot its fathers houſe,</hi> that hath not ſome ſtrong <hi>incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> ſometimes to be <hi>going to its old home againe,</hi> and ſometimes finds not that it hath ſomething to doe to keep his <hi>heart</hi> from (a ſecond time) <hi>embracing</hi> what it hath beene once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Doe you make Chriſt all your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and your ſole delight?</hi> is hee to you <hi>ſolus deſideria, &amp; totus deſideria?</hi> Are your hearts taken more with <hi>Chriſt</hi> than with all the world beſides, and ſo taken with <hi>your husband,</hi> that nothing of him, nor from him, diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth you? can you bee content with <hi>Chriſt alone,</hi> and ſay with <hi>David</hi> to the Lord, <hi>Thou art my portion?</hi> could you queſt all things elſe for him? and is there nothing of him but ſeemes love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to you? doe his ſtricteſt lawes ſeem
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:199320:41"/> excellent to you? Is hee <hi>excellent</hi> to you in the <hi>intent of his Kingly office,</hi> as well as in the <hi>comfort of his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly office?</hi> doth his very <hi>yoke ſeem eaſie,</hi> and his <hi>burthen</hi> ſeem light to you?</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Do you abide with Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>wife abides</hi> with the husband, and <hi>the branch abides in the vine?</hi> every true branch abides in him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 4. is your dwelling with him? or are you onely religious by fits? the hypocrite may bee ſo <hi>religions,</hi> but the Saint makes the Lord <hi>his dwelling place.</hi> Which is that which you count your home? the beſt of Gods Saints may have ſome <hi>inclinations to vanity,</hi> and be ſometimes <hi>trading with the world;</hi> Ah! but Chriſt is his home, Chriſt is his dwelling place; hee thinkes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a <hi>strange place,</hi> when he is not with Chriſt <hi>in duties of holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> Chriſtian, which is thy element? Is your ſoule in its element, when it is converſing with things below Chriſt? that's an ill ſigne, by theſe things you may take a ſcantling of your owne haarts. The Lord help you in applying theſe things to your ſoules. I proceed to a 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> uſe.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:199320:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Here's comfort to the Saints, joy to the upright in heart, eſpecially</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Againſt all the uncomelineſſe and indeſireableneſſe the Saint appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends in himſelfe.</hi> There's none ſo comely as the Saint in Chriſts eyes, nor any ſo uncomely and ugly in their owne eyes; <hi>Paul</hi> cries out, <hi>O wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man that I am,</hi> Rom. 7. 24. and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I am <hi>as one borne out of due time, the leaſt of the Apoſtles, not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be call'd an Apoſtle,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 8, 9. It is an uſuall account the Saints give of themſelves, ah wretched creatures, poore indeſireable wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, hard-hearted ſinners, vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp;c. Bee of good cheare Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, <hi>The King hath deſired thy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> thou art black in thine owne eyes, but comely in Chriſts eyes: <hi>Black</hi> in reſpect of thy merit, but <hi>comely</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of imputation; <hi>comely</hi> through <hi>the comlineſſe</hi> that hee hath put upon you. Secondly,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here's comfort <hi>againſt all the dirt the world caſts upon you, all the uncome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe they conceit in you;</hi> who ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable creatures in the eyes of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199320:42"/> world, as thoſe men and women whom the Lord <hi>delights to honour?</hi> theſe are the deſpiſed ones; upon the backs of theſe it is that <hi>the Plowers plow,</hi> and make <hi>long furrowes;</hi> they are the <hi>upright in heart, that they privily bend their bow to ſhoot at, againſt</hi> theſe are <hi>the puttings out of the fingers,</hi> and the <hi>liftings up of the hands;</hi> upon theſe are laid <hi>all the ſcoffes of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,</hi> and through their weakneſſe the barkings of theſe dogges ſometimes trouble them. But Chriſtians, hath not <hi>the King deſired your beauty?</hi> the beauty that theſe wretches are <hi>ſo blind</hi> they cannot ſee. Hath not the <hi>King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it?</hi> Is it deſireable in Chriſts eyes, and deſpiſed in their eyes? which is the beſt judge, think you? is it not enough for you, that you pleaſe your husband?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here's comfort for you, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt all their ſcoffes, but <hi>againſt all their low eſteeme of you.</hi> David ſaith, <hi>I am ſmall, and of no reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Chriſt was accounted <hi>the leaſt in the kingdome of Heaven;</hi> hee was <hi>the ſtone which the builders refuſed.</hi> A
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:199320:42"/> man of no faſhion in the world, who cared for him? did any of the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees believe</hi> on him? The <hi>wife,</hi> you know, takes her <hi>honour</hi> from her <hi>huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> and uſually, if hee be accounted <hi>one of no faſhion,</hi> ſhee is not valued at a very <hi>high rate;</hi> Saints, though they be indeed the <hi>worlds pillars,</hi> yet in the vulgar <hi>eſtimate</hi> they are the <hi>worlds burthens;</hi> and where ever they live, they uſually live at a <hi>low rate</hi> in <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings deſires,</hi> if any (of <hi>note</hi> before) turne puritane, hee loſeth his <hi>rate</hi> in the <hi>worlds thoughts preſently,</hi> the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman loſeth his <hi>honour,</hi> the <hi>Lady</hi> her <hi>repute;</hi> but it is becauſe their <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> have <hi>loſt their wit,</hi> and their <hi>eyes,</hi> and it need not much trouble a Saint, for Chriſt <hi>deſires</hi> their <hi>beauty</hi> ſtill: They have put themſelves out of the worlds <hi>reckoning,</hi> and heightend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in <hi>Chriſt's eſteem.</hi> Deſpiſe on (fooles) the King hath deſired theſe ſoules beauty,</p>
            <p>Ah! but will a poore miſdoubting Chriſtian ſay, <hi>I am afraid they have a true object of laughter in me. I am afraid I have not that deſireable beauty, but</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:199320:43"/> 
               <hi>am a painted ſepulchre; were I but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that I had indeed truly forgot my fathers houſe, and that the Lord Chriſt had indeed deſired my beauty, I could naile their ſcoffes to my heeles, and mourne over their gallant follies:</hi> But <hi>I feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Obj. <hi>Alas!</hi> I am going home to my fathers houſe ever and anon, I am ready to yield to temptations, ready to fall into ſinne; yea, and the Lord par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don mee, I fall ſeven times a day. If I had forgot my fathers houſe, ſhould I have ſuch inclinations to goe home? would my heart draw ſo hard for vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as it doth ſometimes? ſhould I ſinne ſo often, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I anſw. 1. <hi>Which way ſtands your affection?</hi> your heart you ſay bends that way, but which way ſtands your <hi>affection?</hi> doe you take pleaſure in ſuch <hi>inclinations?</hi> have you a <hi>good mind to ſinne,</hi> if you durſt? to returne to your <hi>old vanities,</hi> if you durſt? only you durſt not, that's an ill ſigne. But upon ſuch <hi>inclinations,</hi> doth there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ariſe a <hi>loathing in your ſoules?</hi> doe you ſay, <hi>Get thee behind mee</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:199320:43"/> 
               <hi>Sathan,</hi> that's a good ſigne, that though you be invited by a <hi>temptation</hi> of <hi>vaine company,</hi> or the <hi>Devill, &amp;c.</hi> yet you have truly <hi>forgotten your fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>You goe home ſometimes you ſay,</hi> it may be you fall into ſome of your former vaine courſes, and are with ſome of your vaine companions. But I pray, <hi>What doe you when you are in your fathers houſe? are you pleaſed with your vanities,</hi> or <hi>with the vanities of your friends?</hi> or doe you ſpend your time <hi>in chiding?</hi> It may be your heart ſometimes <hi>declines to ſome vanity,</hi> or you are ſometimes in <hi>converſe</hi> with <hi>vain perſons.</hi> Are you one with vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, one with ſinners? or doe your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits <hi>riſe againſt your ſelves,</hi> and againſt the <hi>vanities of thoſe with whom you are?</hi> What <hi>indignation</hi> is wrought? if any, you may have <hi>forgot your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe,</hi> for all this <hi>going home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. You goe home ſometimes you ſay. But I pray, <hi>How long doe you ſtay there?</hi> Is ſinne your trade? Doe you <hi>live</hi> in knowne ſinnes? this indeed will argue your <hi>profeſſion</hi> but <hi>hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</hi> But (on the contrary) though
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:199320:44"/> you fall <hi>through weakneſſe,</hi> yet doe you <hi>riſe</hi> through <hi>grace;</hi> though you <hi>ſinne</hi> ſometimes, yet is ſinne as <hi>Davids concupiſcence,</hi> call'd a <hi>ſtranger in the Parable.</hi> Thus the beſt Saints have <hi>ſinn'd,</hi> yea, and <hi>may ſinne;</hi> not of <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,</hi> but of <hi>weakneſſe;</hi> not <hi>trading in ſinne,</hi> nor <hi>lying</hi> in it, but <hi>falling into it,</hi> and <hi>riſing by repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Obj. <hi>Ah! but will another Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſay,</hi> I cannot deny my ſelfe in the company of my fathers houſe, wretch that I am. I got acquaintance when I was young with vaine perſons, or I am related to ſuch, and I dare not ſay, but I love their company, and oft times leave better for them; neither can I deny my ſelfe in my relations. My heart is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively let out after them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thou ſaieſt thou art oft times yet a companion of vaine perſons, but conſider (Chriſtian) are they <hi>thy invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted gheſts,</hi> or accidentall meerly? are they <hi>intruders,</hi> or are they the <hi>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come crmpanions</hi> of thy life? are they thy <hi>pickt company</hi> or no, thy <hi>intimates,</hi> or meerly <hi>companions</hi> in reſpect of thy <hi>trade,</hi> and <hi>converſe with the world?</hi> If
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:199320:44"/> thou delighteſt not in them, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are ſometimes thy companions, but thou art not theirs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Art thou a companion with them in ſinne, or onely in civill actions, or for diſcourſe, &amp;c. ſometimes?</hi> if the firſt indeed it is a ſigne thou haſt not left thy fathers houſe; but if the latter onely, it is no ſuch ſigne, thou keepeſt thy courſe, they come to thee, and it may be <hi>diſturbe</hi> thee, but thou doeſt not goe to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thou ſayeſt thou loveſt them. But it would be conſidered, <hi>Whether thy love be meerly naturall or more?</hi> It may be thou loveſt them becauſe they are <hi>witty people,</hi> or of <hi>ingenuous diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</hi> Thus Chriſt loved the <hi>young man, Matth.</hi> 19. and thus thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt love them. It is an ill ſigne, if thou loveſt them, becauſe they will <hi>drinke,</hi> or <hi>ſweare,</hi> or bee <hi>vain and wanton</hi> in their <hi>diſcourſe</hi> or <hi>carriages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Thou ſayeſt thou loveſt thy rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and thou canſt not deny thy ſelfe in them, thy heart is ſo <hi>glued</hi> to them, &amp;c. and God forbid but thou ſhouldſt <hi>love</hi> them, 1. <hi>with a naturall</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:199320:45"/> 
               <hi>affection,</hi> its a ſigne of a wretch, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 31. to be <hi>without naturall affection,</hi> and 2. <hi>with a providentiall love and care;</hi> hee that <hi>provides not for his family</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) is <hi>worſe than an infidell.</hi> But 1. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Chriſt ſhould call thee to ſuffer for him, and</hi> thou hadſt a good mind to it, and they ſhould plead hard for thee to <hi>ſpare thy ſelfe;</hi> wouldſt thou with <hi>Hierom ſhake off thy father, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and children, and runne to Chriſt?</hi> this would bee a ſigne thou hadſt <hi>for-got them,</hi> Though thou loveſt them. 2. Notwithſtanding that thou loveſt them, <hi>wouldſt thou favour them in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinne againſt God, and onely luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmely reprove them,</hi> like old <hi>Elie? It is not well done of you, O my ſons,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou loveſt them: wilt thou ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let them <hi>diſhonour God, damn</hi> their <hi>owne ſoules,</hi> doe any thing, rather than <hi>reprove,</hi> or <hi>ſmite them?</hi> this love indeed is a <hi>reall hatred,</hi> and will argue <hi>little love to God in thy ſoule.</hi> But on the contrary, though thou <hi>loveſt them</hi> with the <hi>tendereſt love,</hi> &amp; wilt <hi>provide</hi> for them with the moſt <hi>providential</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:199320:45"/> 
               <hi>care;</hi> yet is thy love ſo truly <hi>tempered,</hi> that it ſhall not in the leaſt hinder thee from <hi>doing thy duty to Chriſt;</hi> no, nor yet from <hi>doing thy duty to them;</hi> from <hi>reproving ſharply, admoniſhing ſeverely?</hi> is thy love ſuch, that it ſhall not <hi>blind thy eyes,</hi> ſo as thou wilt <hi>wink at the leaſt neglect of duty</hi> in them, not at the leaſt ſin-in them? Love them then as wel as thou canſt, it ſhall be no ſad <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> againſt thy <hi>ſoule,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>(Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> look to it) your children will curſe you another day for your <hi>love to them:</hi> you have heard of <hi>killing with kindneſſe;</hi> let the kind of death be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſweet, yet the death will be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Take heed not of <hi>killing the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> (alas, that were nothing) but of <hi>damning</hi> your <hi>childrens ſoules,</hi> and your owne too, with <hi>miſcalled kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 Obj. <hi>But wil another Chriſtian ſay,</hi> I have not forgot my honour and glory, I am not low enough, I feare, to get in at heavens <hi>gate. I anſwer firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This is like <hi>the melancholy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of her, that a Divine of our owne ſpeaks</hi> of; <hi>of a woman that conceited,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:199320:46"/> 
               <hi>ſhe was ſo fat, ſhee could not get to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> it is the <hi>lowneſſe</hi> of mind that God looks at, <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Ladies,</hi> if their hearts be not as <hi>high</hi> as their <hi>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles,</hi> may ſit in heaven as well as mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner perſons. I doe not ſay, they ſhall have chaires of ſtate ſet for them, but they may have a roome there; it may be one or two may ſit above them (if there bee degrees in glory) that gave them place here: but as Maſter <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therford</hi> ſayes, <hi>the leaſt place in Heaven is Heaven, though it bee behind the doore.</hi> But ſecondly,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Is not thy outward Pompe and glory that which thou affecteſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt in it, and hunteſt after?</hi> Does not thy title <hi>tickle</hi> thy eare, nor <hi>ſwell thy heart,</hi> if not, it can <hi>doe thee no hurt?</hi> all the feare of thoſe <hi>ſwelling things is,</hi> leſt they ſhould breed <hi>tympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in the ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Doe you look upon the title of the ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, the title of Chriſtian, as the farre more honourable title?</hi> Are you of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which would you rather chuſe, to be call'd <hi>my Lord,</hi> or <hi>Madam,</hi> or to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199320:46"/> be called the <hi>ſervant of Chriſt;</hi> which doe you preferre? if the latter, it is a ſigne you have forgot the former, though you retaine it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Is your outward greatneſſe and pompe no ſnare to your ſoule in the wayes of God?</hi> Great perſons are too ready to think they are above <hi>prayers,</hi> above <hi>hearing,</hi> above <hi>meane Saints;</hi> ſhould ſuch ones as they pray in their families; no, let their boy do it? ſhould they pray in ſecret, and runne up and downe to <hi>lectures?</hi> O no (forſooth) it is a diſhononour to them (Heaven was made, I confeſſe, for the moſt part, for people of leſſer quality, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 26, 27. <hi>James</hi> 2. 5.) ſhould ſuch as they go to private meetings? no, better go to a taverne, there they ſhall only <hi>foule their ſoules,</hi> but <hi>keep their clothes cleane.</hi> But now, hath the Lord given thee <hi>another ſpirit?</hi> it is true, thou art great, but thy great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is no ſuch <hi>ſnare to thy ſoule;</hi> thou canſt <hi>pray for all thy greatneſſe,</hi> and <hi>heare ſermons,</hi> and <hi>kneele in a duty</hi> for all thy <hi>ſilk ſtockings,</hi> and entertain <hi>communion with the meaneſt Saint;</hi> yea,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:199320:47"/> and for a need <hi>preferre a lether dublet in honour before thy ſelfe.</hi> Though thou beeſt great it ſeemes thou haſt forgot it.</p>
            <p>4 Obj. <hi>Ah, but will a Chriſtian ſay,</hi> I am ſo addicted to mirth, and pleaſure; I muſt have my vagary, and tickle my ſenſe ſometimes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Anſw. <hi>Chriſtian, doſt thou love thy pleaſures more than thy God,</hi> that indeed were ſomething? art thou more pleaſed with hearing <hi>a ſong,</hi> than hearing a <hi>ſermon?</hi> this ſounds high. But love God beſt, and for ought I know, thy eye (for thy recreation) may bee delighted in <hi>ſeeing,</hi> and thy <hi>eare</hi> with <hi>hearing</hi> too.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Anſw. <hi>Wilt thou baulk an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of communion with Chriſt, or with his Saints, for a vaine pleaſure?</hi> Wilt thou bee a loſer in thy heart, to gaine a little pleaſure for thine <hi>eye,</hi> or <hi>eare,</hi> or any ſenſe? wilt thou miſſe a <hi>family duty,</hi> an <hi>opportunity of hearing Gods word privatly or publiquely,</hi> thy time of ſecret duty, a time of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Saints to wait upon thy pleaſure? In ſuch a caſe I would have
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199320:47"/> thee ſuſpect thy heart, otherwiſe thou mayeſt recreate thy ſelfe with them, and yet have forgotten them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Anſw. <hi>Suppoſe thy pleaſures have been ſuch, and are ſuch, as are in themſelves ſinfull,</hi> as <hi>wantonneſſe, drunkenneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Doſt thou love them ſo, that thou wilt have them whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God will or no? thou wilt break with God to enjoy thy luſt; this is an ill, and a very ill ſigne. But poſſibly thy pleaſures are ſuch as God <hi>allowes thee</hi> (temperately uſed) if ſuch, thou mayeſt ſo uſe them, and yet the <hi>King deſire thy beauty.</hi> I have finiſhed this branch of application, I have but one word more to adde: It ſhall be of</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Exhortation.</hi> Let mee now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade with you Chriſtians; And (oh that the Lord would help mee to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade) 1. with you, <hi>who have not at all yet forgate your fathers houſe,</hi> and ſo conſequently, <hi>your beauty is not at all deſirable to Chriſt.</hi> 2. <hi>With you that have begun to doe well;</hi> I have a word to both ſorts,</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Br.</hi> Is there, alas, is there any poore ſoule before me this day, whoſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:199320:48"/> heart ſmites him, and tells him, that his ſoule is not at all yet <hi>deſirable in the eyes of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> is there any poore creature ſo ſadly miſerable? poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly the world dotes on you for <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wit, parts, behaviour, &amp;c.</hi> but in the meane time, doe your ſoules, tell you in plaine Engliſh, that you are <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed in Chriſts eyes. As though God did beſeech you by mee, I pray you in Chriſts ſtead be reconciled to God.</hi> Ah poore ſoule, wouldſt thou be deſired of Jeſus Chriſt? <hi>Hearken then O daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and conſider, and incline your care, forget thy owne people, and thy fathers houſe.</hi> I know I am pleading with you for an hard thing, eſpecially for you that have all the world at will: But I beſeech you <hi>by the love you bear to your precious ſoules,</hi> which ſhall laſt for ever; doe it, ah doe it. I had need now have the Rhethorick of an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell,</hi> yea, if I had; yet <hi>God muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Japhet to come and dwell in the tents of Shem.</hi> Let mee offer but a few conſiderations, and venture at a perſwading of you, and leave the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue with God.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:199320:48"/> 1. Conſider, <hi>How will you live when your fathers houſe failes you?</hi> for the preſent it <hi>is a full houſe,</hi> and you live, as wee ſay, as well as a carnall heart would wiſh; you have <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> and <hi>honours,</hi> and <hi>riches,</hi> even what you would aske: the colour is in your <hi>cheeks,</hi> and the <hi>marow in your bones.</hi> But will this laſt alwayes? <hi>doth not the faſhion of this world paſſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way? and will not the faſhion of your bodies paſſe away? what will you doe in that day of your viſitation? Theſe things may laſt a <hi>while,</hi> till God comes to keep <hi>a Court in your Conſcience,</hi> or hee ſummons you to a <hi>particular judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or layes you upon your back <hi>in a bed of affliction,</hi> or comes to <hi>his laſt judgement:</hi> But in any of theſe dayes (poore creature) what wilt thou doe? when thy <hi>perfumed body</hi> ſhall come to <hi>ſtinke in the noſtrils of men,</hi> thy ſoule ſhall be more <hi>loathed of God;</hi> a future livelihood would be thought of, This will perſwade a virgin to marry ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. But beſides.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſtian, <hi>Doſt thou know the joyes of a married life to Chriſt?</hi> doſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:199320:49"/> thou put no difference betwixt being a <hi>bondſlave to hell,</hi> and one free in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; betwixt the enjoying the communion of the children of the Devill, and enjoying the communion of Saints? no difference betwixt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the commun on of devils, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting torments, and the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of God, Angells, and Saints, in the higheſt Heavens, <hi>where eye hath not ſeen, nor hath eare heard, nor can it enter into the heart of man, to conceive what things God hath prepared for them that love him?</hi> now (if thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bee not ſeared) thou haſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and anon <hi>ſome flaſhes of hell in thy face.</hi> The merrieſt ſinner of you all, I believe is not alwayes free. Is there no difference betwixt that condition, think you, and a peace of conſcience, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt? Now, you never lie downe in your beds, but (if you dare look back, and conſider how you have ſpent the day) your ſoule is ſtricken with <hi>terrour,</hi> and there is a <hi>dart almoſt ſtruck through</hi> your <hi>liver,</hi> and you dare not let your ſoules feed upon the thoughts, but are glad
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:199320:49"/> to <hi>ſhuffle it over,</hi> for feare you <hi>runne madde;</hi> but if your ſoules would but forget theſe vanities, ah, how ſweetly would you ſleep; and when you had ſpent <hi>a day in duties</hi> of hearing or praying, how ſweetly would your ſoules look back upon it. Now if you were not rock't into a ſleep of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you would ſcarce lie downe to ſleep, but you would feare leſt you ſhould wake in the morning with <hi>hell flames about your eares;</hi> nor walke in the day, but (like the ſelfe-accuſed murtherer) your eye would be over your ſhoulder, for feare the devill ſhould be laying hold of you: then you would <hi>lie downe in peace,</hi> and <hi>riſe up in peace,</hi> and nothing would <hi>make you afraid.</hi> Is this world nothing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian? ah, that the Lord would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you of this. Beſides,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider (Chriſtian) <hi>there is nothing in your fathers houſe but you ſhall find in Chriſt, by a way of eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> Muſt you forſake your ſinnes, you ſhall be <hi>filled with the graces of the ſpirit of God?</hi> Muſt you forſake a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:199320:50"/> idle <hi>vaine company,</hi> you ſhall have the <hi>communion of Saints,</hi> yea, a <hi>fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the father, and the ſonne the Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> 1 Joh. 1. 3. Muſt you forget your pompe and glory, &amp;c. you ſhall bee called <hi>the ſonnes and daughters of God, heires, coheires</hi> with <hi>Christ?</hi> Rom. 8. Muſt you forget worldly riches, you ſhall have the <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of grace?</hi> Muſt you forget a few vaine pleaſures, you ſhall have a <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of pleaſures,</hi> at Chriſts right <hi>hand, and that for evermore?</hi> Pſal. 16. 11. Muſt you forget your owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, you ſhall bee clothed with the <hi>righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> what's loſt by the exchange Chriſtian?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider againe, <hi>Chriſt forgot his fathers houſe for you,</hi> and yet it was worth many of yours; hee forgot the <hi>glory,</hi> the <hi>company,</hi> the <hi>pleaſures</hi> of his <hi>fathers houſe</hi> for you; he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, for you, to be a <hi>companion</hi> of <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhermen,</hi> yea, of <hi>ſinners,</hi> yea, of <hi>theeves,</hi> when he <hi>died upon the croſſe</hi> for you: this he did freely, <hi>he made himſelfe of no reputation,</hi> hee <hi>nothinged</hi> himſelfe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:199320:50"/> for you: Hark what the Apoſtle ſayes, 2 Cor. 8. 9. <hi>you know the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who though he was rich, yet for your ſake hee became poore; that you through his poverty might be made rich.</hi> Let that melting love winne you. Beſides,</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>It is the way to be beautifull:</hi> what abundance of paines poor vaine wretches take to be beautifull? ſurely this muſt move. <hi>Beauty</hi> is a <hi>deſirable thing,</hi> the vaine creatures of the earth would never elſe ſet nature with the heeles upward, doe any thing to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it; wee ſhould never elſe have ſo much <hi>precious time loſt,</hi> and ſo many <hi>precious ſoules undone</hi> with paintings, and trimmings, patchings, and perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings, and a thouſand ſuch apiſh tricks: but beauty is the <hi>idoll of the world,</hi> to which the very ſoule ſhall be <hi>offered up in ſacrifice,</hi> and when all this is done the ſoule is <hi>amiſſe,</hi> and the way to adorne that, is to <hi>undreſſe all</hi> againe. Hark, you that deſire beauty, here's the way of beauty which <hi>you have not known;</hi> it is to deny your ſelves in all
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:199320:51"/> theſe things, and whatſoever elſe is contrary to the <hi>law of Chriſt,</hi> or ſhort of him; yea, and this,</p>
            <p n="6">6. Shall make you <hi>deſirably beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> that Chriſt ſhall deſire you, and the Saints ſhall deſire you; this is the way to raviſh his heart. But no more by way of motive, God muſt doe all I know when I have ſpake my ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt.</p>
            <p>I might tell you who it is will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your beauty; <hi>It is the King of heaven,</hi> of <hi>glory,</hi> and <hi>peace;</hi> the <hi>King ſhall deſire your beauty.</hi> If this, all this will not doe, the Lord open your eyes, and then I am ſure it will.</p>
            <p>But this is an hard work, and young ones eſpecially had need of a great deale of helpe to it, and truly nature affords none, all is laid up in Chriſt onely; In order to the getting of it from Chriſt, let me adviſe you;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>1</label> Firſt, <hi>With a ſerious eye to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your fathers houſe,</hi> and ſee what there is in it <hi>deſirable,</hi> that ſhould ſo bewitch one that hath not <hi>outlawed</hi> his or her <hi>reaſon to it.</hi> Look ſeriouſly
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:199320:51"/> upon your <hi>ſinnes,</hi> will you not ſee a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe in them? Look upon your <hi>vaine company,</hi> bee they what they will, will you not diſcerne ſome <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didneſſe</hi> or <hi>baſeneſſe</hi> in their actions? upon your <hi>honours</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> will they not appeare <hi>bubbles?</hi> upon your <hi>pleaſures,</hi> will they not appeare <hi>ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes?</hi> You look upon theſe things as <hi>pictures,</hi> ſide-wayes, or at a <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> that makes you admire them, and runne after them: come nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to them, will they not look <hi>daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with ſome uncomelineſſe or other?</hi> Will not the <hi>colours</hi> that look'd ſo <hi>ſweetly afarre off, ſtink</hi> if you bring them <hi>neere</hi> your <hi>noſe?</hi> Let that bee the firſt piece of advice.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>While you enjoy theſe things, take heed of letting out your heart to them;</hi> rejoyce <hi>as if you rejoyced not,</hi> and <hi>uſe the world as if you uſed it not;</hi> be not too much intent upon <hi>your fathers houſe,</hi> converſe not too much with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing there; things of the world have a <hi>glutinous quality,</hi> the heart <hi>will cleave to them,</hi> if you let it lie very
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:199320:52"/> long amongſt them; and if it once cleaves, there will bee no wayes, but either your heart muſt be ſoundly rent upon the ſevering, or hell-fire muſt part them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, Ah, <hi>Learne to live from your fathers houſe betimes,</hi> take the wiſe mans counſell, it was after a large <hi>ſurvey</hi> and <hi>diſcourſe of every roome,</hi> and the <hi>vanity of every roome in our fathers houſe,</hi> Eccl. 12. 1. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth;</hi> if <hi>rottenneſſe</hi> enter into the <hi>bones,</hi> it will hardly <hi>ever out.</hi> You that are young, for the Lords ſake think of this: Ah, come off your youthfull va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities before they can plead <hi>cuſtome</hi> with your ſoules, live <hi>from home</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, believe it, there will bee more weeping elſe when you come to part.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>4</label> Laſtly, <hi>Crie, crie mightily unto God, that he would take off your heart:</hi> Believe it, it muſt be his work, you will be wearied elſe <hi>in the multitude of your owne indeavours;</hi> if the Lord draw off the heart, it will be drawne
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:199320:52"/> indeed. Be much in <hi>publique prayer,</hi> but eſpecially be much in <hi>ſecret prayer.</hi> I muſt conclude.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Br.</hi> Laſtly, you that have been taught of the Lord to forget your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, that ſo the King might deſire your beauty, Let mee plead with you <hi>ſtill to forget it more.</hi> Selfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniall is a <hi>long</hi> and <hi>hard leſſon,</hi> a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian muſt be learning it from his <hi>cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> to his <hi>grave,</hi> and every time hee ſtudies it hee ſhall find ſomething to be done that is yet behind, and all that he hath done to bee done better: you have learned in part how to doe it, I need not direct you, you need no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directions then</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To ſtudy every day more and more the vanitie of the creature.</hi> Read over the book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> well, it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to teach you that leſſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Converſe little with your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe,</hi> have as little to doe with the world, the <hi>pleaſures,</hi> or <hi>profits,</hi> or <hi>riches,</hi> or <hi>companie,</hi> or <hi>manners</hi> of it as you can, the leſſer the better.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Be more acquainted with Jeſus</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:199320:53"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> get neerer to him, bee more in <hi>communion</hi> with him, get more <hi>tasts of Heaven,</hi> Earth will <hi>reliſh</hi> the worſe for it. I might preſſe upon you the ſame motives I urged before, and I ſhould doe it with advantages; you know what <hi>this King is,</hi> how much to bee <hi>deſired,</hi> how much to bee <hi>odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               </hi>red; you know what a difference there is betwixt the worlds <hi>comelineſſe,</hi> and the <hi>comelineſſe which hee putteth upon his Saints.</hi> Let mee onely urge one word, or rather name it:</p>
            <p>Some read the words, <hi>quia concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit,</hi> Becauſe the King hath deſired thy beauty, here's an argument, an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging argument to a Saint. The Lord hath effectually made it knowne in your ſoules, that hee deſires your beauty more than tenne thouſands of others. Hee hath whiſpered, not onely in your eares, but in your heart, his deſire to you. Ah, now Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans be you humble, ſelf-denying ones, <hi>becauſe the King hath deſired your beauty.</hi> Let the love of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine you, to order your <hi>hearts</hi> and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:199320:53"/> 
               <hi>converſations</hi> as <hi>becommeth the Goſpell of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> According to the lawes of this King that hath ſo <hi>paſſionately deſired,</hi> and ſo <hi>effecaciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly declared his deſire</hi> to your <hi>beauty.</hi> I muſt have done: The Lord adde his bleſſing.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
